<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Batchellors banquet, or, A banquet for batchellors wherein is prepared sundry dainty dishes to furnish their tables curiously drest and seriously served in : [p]leasantly discoursing the variable humours of women, their quickness of wits and unsearchable deceits.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27945</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B259</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25901</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09279951</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09279951</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42603</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27945)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42603)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1299:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Batchellors banquet, or, A banquet for batchellors wherein is prepared sundry dainty dishes to furnish their tables curiously drest and seriously served in : [p]leasantly discoursing the variable humours of women, their quickness of wits and unsearchable deceits.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[67] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edward Thomas,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An adaptation of "Quinze joyes de mariage," 15th century French satire on women.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriage.</term>
               <term>Women --  Anecdotes</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42603:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Batchellors Banquet</hi> OR, A Banquet for Batchellors, Wherein is prepared ſundry dainty diſhes to furniſh their tables, curiouſly dreſt, and ſeriouſly ſerved in.</p>
            <p>Pleaſantly diſcourſing the variable humours of Women, their quickneſs of wits, and unſearchable deceits.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>View them well, but taſte not,</l>
               <l>Regard them well, but waſte not.</l>
            </lg>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Edward Thomas</hi> at the <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in <hi>Little-Brittain,</hi> 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:42603:2"/>
            <lg>
               <l>You Batchellors that with us mean to feaſt,</l>
               <l>Come all and welcome to our homely fare;</l>
               <l>If at our Banquet you will be a Gueſt,</l>
               <l>Here at our furniſht Table take a ſhare:</l>
               <l>Our Ordinary is but ſix pence price.</l>
               <l>Variety of diſhes, be not nice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We muſt confeſs our board it is not ſpread</l>
               <l>As is the married mans, with Carp and Lout;</l>
               <l>We do not uſe to feed upon Cods-head,</l>
               <l>Crabs, Ill-pies, Gudgeon, nor the dogged Pout:</l>
               <l>For fleſh, we taſte no Souſe, no Lomb, no Quail,</l>
               <l>No Woodcock, Wigeon, Bittern, Gooſe nor Rail.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For our laſt ſervice, we feed not on Chuſe;</l>
               <l>Small-reaſons, Bitter-almonds, nor choak-pears;</l>
               <l>We eat the beſt, and do the worſt refuſe,</l>
               <l>Have good content, and ſing away ſad cares:</l>
               <l>Good diet, Engliſh beer, and Spaniſh ſherry,</l>
               <l>Come Batchellors then let us all be merry.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:42603:2"/>
            <head>The Batchellors Banquet: Or a Banquet for Batchellors: wherin is prepared ſundry diſhes to furniſh their Table: Curiouſly dreſt, and ſeriouſly ſerved in.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. The humour of a young wife new married.</head>
               <p>IT is the natural inclination of a young Gallant in the pleaſant prime, and flower of his flouriſhing youth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing freſh luſty and jocond, to take no other care but to imploy his money to buy gay preſents for pretty laſſes, to frame his green wits in penning love Ditties, his voice to ſing them ſweetly, his wandring eyes to gaze on the faireſt dames and his wanton thoughts to plot means for the ſpeedy accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of his wiſhed deſires, according to the compaſs of his eſtate. And albeit his parents or ſome other of his kinred, do perhaps fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh him with neceſſary maintenance, ſo that he wants nothing, but lives in all eaſe &amp; delight; yet cannot this content him, or ſatiſfie his unexperienced mind: for although he daily ſee many married men firſt lapt in lobs pound, wanting former liberty, and compaſſed round in a a cage of many cares, yet notwithſtanding over-ruled by ſelf-will, and blind by folly he ſuppoſes them therein to have the fulneſſe of their delight, becauſe they have ſo near them the Image of content <hi>Venus</hi> ſtar gloriouſly blazing upon them, I mean a dainty fair wife bravely attired, whoſe apparel perhaps is not yet paid for, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever (to draw their husband into a fools paradiſe) they make them believe that their father or mother have of their coſt, &amp; bounty afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it. This luſty youth (as I earſt ſaid) ſeeing them already in this maze of bitter ſweetneſs, he goes round about, turmoyling himſelf in ſeeking an entrance, and taking ſuch pains to find his own pain, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the end, in he gets, when for the haſt he makes to have a taſte of theſe ſuppoſed delicates he hath no leiſure to think, or no care to provide thoſe things that are hereunto requiſite. The jolly Yonker being thus gotten in, doth for a time ſwim in delight, and hath no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb facs="tcp:42603:3"/>at all to winde himſelf out again, till time and uſe which makes all things more familiar and leſs pleaſing, do qualifie this humour: then glutted with ſatiety, or pinched with penury, he may perhaps begin to ſee his folly, &amp; repent as well his fundneſs, as his too much forwardneſſe, but all too late, he muſt have patience perforce: his wife muſt be maintained according to her degree, and withall (commonly it haps ſhe carries the right ſtomach of a Woman) ſlender mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence will not ſerve, for as their minds mount above their eſtates, ſo commonly they will have their abiliments. And if at a feaſt or ſome other goſſips meeting whereunto ſhe is invited, ſhe ſee any of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany gaily attired for coſt or faſhion, or both, or chiefly the latter, for generally women do affect novelties, ſhe forthwith moves a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion in her ſelf, why ſhe alſo ſhould not be in the like ſort attired, to have her garments cut after the new faſhion as well as the reſt, and anſwers it with reſolution, that ſhe will and muſt have the like: A wating onely fit time and place for the moving and winning of her husband thereunto, of both which ſhe will make ſuch choice, that when ſhe ſpeaks ſhe will be ſure to ſpeed; obſerving her opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty when ſhe might take her husband at the moſt advantage, which is commonly the garden of love, the ſtate of marriage delights, and the life wherein the weaker ſex hath ever the better: when therefore this luſty Gallant would fulfill his deſire, for which cauſe he chiefly ran wilfully into the peril of lobs pound, then ſqueamiſhly ſhe begins thus, ſaying, I pray you husband let me alone, trouble me not, for I am not well at eaſe: which he hearing, preſently makes this reply.</p>
               <p>Why my ſweet heart what ailes you, are you not well: I pray thee wife tell me, where lies thy grief? or what is the cauſe of your diſcontent? whereupon the vile woman fetching a deep ſigh makes this anſwer? O Husband, God help me, I have cauſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to grieve, and if you knew all you would ſay ſo: but alas it is in vain to tell you any thing, ſeeing that whatſoever I ſay, you make but little reckoning of it: and therefore it is beſt for me to bury my ſorrows in ſilence, being out of hope to have any help at your hands. Ieſus, wife (ſaith he) why uſe you theſe words? is my unkindneſs ſuch, that I may not know your grief: tell me I ſay, what is the matter? In truth husband it were to no purpoſe, for I know your cuſtome well enough; as for my words they are but waſte winde in your ears, for how great ſoever my grief is, I am
<pb facs="tcp:42603:3"/>aſſured you will but make light of it, and think that I ſpeak it for ſome other purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Go to Wife, ſaith her husband, tell it me, for I will know it. Well husband, if you will needs, you ſhall. You know on <hi>Thurſday</hi> laſt, I was ſent for, and you willed me to go to Miſtreſs <hi>M.</hi> Churching, and when I came thither, I found great cheer, and no ſmall company of wives, but the meaneſt of them all was not ſo ill attired as I, and ſurely I, was never ſo aſhamed of my ſelf in my life: Yet I ſpeak it not to praiſe my ſelf, but it is well known, and I dare boldly ſay, that the beſt women there, came of no better ſtock than I. But alas, I ſpeak not this for my ſelf, for God wot I paſs not how meanly I am apparelled, but I ſpeak it for your credit, and my friends. Why Wife, ſaith he, of what calling and degree were thoſe you ſpeak of? Truely good Husband (ſaith ſhe) the meaneſt that was there, being but of my degree, was in her looſe Gown, with hanging ſleeves, her French Roſes, her Silk Grograine Kirtle, her Bever Hat, with a Gold Band, and theſe with the reſt of her attire, made of the neweſt faſhion which is known the beſt: Whereas I poor wretch had on my thred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare Gown, which was made me ſo long agoe, againſt I was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, beſides that it was now too ſhort for me, for it is I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſince it was made about three years agoe, ſince which time I am grown very much, and ſo changed with cares and griefs, that I look far older then I am: Truſt me, I was ſo aſhamed, being amongſt my neighbours, that I had not the heart to look up, but that which grieved me moſt was when Miſtreſs <hi>Luce B.</hi> and Miſtreſs <hi>T.</hi> ſaid openly that it was a ſhame both for you and me, that I had no better Apparel. Tuſh Wife (quoth the good man) let them ſay what they liſt, we are never a whit the worſe for their words, we have enough to doe with our money, though we ſpend it not in Apparell: You know Wife, when we met together, we had no great ſtore of Houſhold-ſtuff, but were fain to buy it afterward by ſome and ſome, as God ſent money, and yet you ſee wee want many things that are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be had: Beſides the Quarter Day is neer, and my Landlord you know will not forbear his Rent: Moreover, you ſee how much it coſts me in Law about the recovering of the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement which I ſhould have by you: God ſend me to get it quickly,
<pb facs="tcp:42603:4"/>or elſe I ſhall have but a bad bargain of it, for it hath already almoſt coſt me as much as it is worth. At theſe words his Wives choler be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to riſe, whereupon ſhe makes him this anſwer. Goodly, goodly, (ſaith ſhe) when you have nothing elſe to hit me in the teeth withall, yee twit me with the tenement; but it is my fortune. Why how now Wife ſaith her Husband, are you now angry for nothing Nay, I am not angry, I muſt be content with that which God hath ordained for me: But I wis the time was, when I might have been better adviſed, there are ſome yet living that would have been glad to have me in my ſmock, whom you know well enough to be proper young men and therewithall wiſe and wealthy: but I verily ſuppoſe I was bewicht to match witch a man that loves me not: though I purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ill will of all my friends for his ſake, this is all the good that I have gotten thereby: I may truly ſay I am the moſt unhappy Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the world: Doe you think that <hi>Law. Tom.</hi> and <hi>N. M.</hi> (who were both ſuters to me) do keep their Wives ſo? no by lady, for I know the worſt cloths that they caſt off, are better than my very beſt which I wear on the chiefeſt dayes in the year: I know not what the cauſe is that ſo many good women dye, but I would to God that I were dead too, that I might trouble you no more, ſeeing I am ſuch an eye ſore unto you. Now by my faith wife, ſaith he, you ſay not well, there is nothing that I think too good for you, if my ability can compaſs it. But you know our eſtate, we muſt do as we may, and not as we would, yet be of good cheer, and I will ſtrain my ſelf to pleaſe you, in this or any other thing.</p>
               <p>Nay, I have no mind on ſuch matters, and if you had no more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thereto than I, I promiſe you, you would never touch me. No Wife (ſaith he) hoping ſo with a jeſt to make her merry, by my hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty I ſwear, I verily think that if I were dead, you would not be long without another husband. No marvel ſure ſaith ſhe, I lead ſuch a good life with you now, By my Chriſtian ſoul I ſwear, there ſhould never a man kiſs my lips again. And if I thought I ſhould live long with you, I would uſe means to make my ſelf away: Herewithall ſhe puts finger in the eye, making ſhew as though ſhe wept: Thus playes ſhe with the ſilly ſot her husband (meaning no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe than to do as ſhe ſayes) while he poor fool is in mind both well and ill apaid: he thinks himſelf well, becauſe he imagines her of a cold conſtitution, and therefore exceeding chaſt: he thinks
<pb facs="tcp:42603:4"/>himſelf ill, to ſee her fained tears, for that he verily ſuppoſes ſhe loves him, which doth not a little grieve him, being ſo kind and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hearted. Therefore he uſeth all means poſſible to make her quiet, never will he give her over, while he hath effected it. But ſhe proſecuting her former purpoſe which ſhe hath already ſet in ſo fair a forwardneſſe, makes as though ſhe were nothing moved with his gentle perſwaſions: Therefore to croſſe him, ſhe gets her up betimes in the morning, ſooner a great deal than ſhe was wont, powting and lowring, all the day, and not giving him one good word. But when night comes, and they again both in bed, laying her ſelf ſullenly down, and continuing ſtill ſilent, the good man hearkens whether ſhe ſleep or no, feels if ſhe be well covered or not, he ſoftly pluckes up the clothes upon her, lapping her warm, being double diligent to pleaſe her. She lying all this while winking, noring his kindneſſe and carefulneſſe towards her, feems on a ſudden to awake from a ſound ſleep, gruntling and nuſling under the ſheets giving him occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereby thus to begin. How now ſweet heart, what are you aſleep? Aſleep (ſaith ſhe) faith Sir no: a troubled mind can never take good reſt. Why woman are you not quiet yet? No doubt (ſaith ſhe) you care much whether I be or no. By lady wife and ſo I do: and ſince yeſternight, I have bethought me (having well conſidered your words) that it is very meet and requiſite, that you ſhould be better furniſhed with apparell than heretofore you have been, for indeed I muſt confeſſe thy cloths are too ſimple; and therefore I mean a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my couſin <hi>M.</hi> wedding (which you know will be ſhortly) that you ſhall have a new gown made on the beſt faſhion, with all things ſuitable thereunto, in ſuch ſort that the beſt woman in the pariſh ſhall not paſſe you. Nay (quoth ſhe) God willing I mean to go to no weddings this twelve moneth, for the goodly credit I got by the laſt By my faith (ſaith he) but you ſhall, what? you muſt not be ſo head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong and ſelf-willed. I tell you if I ſay the word you ſhall go, and you ſhall want nothing that you ask or require. That I ask? alas husband (quoth ſhe) I ask nothing, neither did I ſpeak this for any deſire that I have to go brave, truſt me, for my own part I care not if I never ſtir abroad ſave onely to Church: but what I ſaid was upon the ſpeeches which were there uſed, and ſuch other like words, which my Goſſip <hi>N.</hi> told me that ſhe had alſo heard in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany where ſhe was. With theſe words the good kind fool her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band
<pb facs="tcp:42603:5"/>is netled, for on the one ſide he conſiders his ſundry other occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to uſe money &amp; his ſmall ſtore thereof, which is perhaps ſo ſlender, that his ſingle purſe cannot <hi>extempore</hi> change a double piſtolet. And ſo ill beſted of houſhold ſtuff, that perhaps the third part is not a ſufficient pawn for ſo much money as this new ſute of his Wives will ſtand him in. But one the other ſide he weighs her diſcontent, the report of neighbours ſpeeches, and laſtly how good a Wife he hath of her, how chaſt, how loving, how religio us, whereof the kind Aſſe hath ſuch an opinion, that he thanks God with all his heart, for bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him with ſuch a Iewel: In this thought he reſolves that all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things ſet aſide, he muſt and will content her. And herewithall he ſets his brains afreſh on work, to conſider how beſt he may compaſs it: And in this humour he ſpends the whole night without ſleep, in continual thought. And it comes to paſs that the Wife per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving to what a point ſhe hath brought her purpoſe, doth not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle rejoyce and ſmile in her ſleeve to ſee it. The next morning by the break of day the poor man gets up who for care and thought could take no reſt all night, and goes preſently to the Drapers, of whom he takes up cloath for three moneths time, paying for it after an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecſſive rate, by reaſon of their forbearance, and in like ſort makes proviſion for the reſt; for perhaps becauſe he would buy it at a better rate, he pawns for ready money the Leaſe of his houſe, or ſome fair piece of plate, which his grandfather bought, and his father charily keeping, left for him which now he is enforced to part with, to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh thereby his wives pride; and having thus diſpatched his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he returns home with a merry heart, and ſhews his Wife what he hath done: who being now ſure of all, begins to curſe the firſt inventers of pride, and exceſs in apparel: ſaying, Fie upon it, what pride is this? but I pray you husband, do not ſay hereafter that I made you lay out your money in this needleſs ſort, for I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt that I have no delight or deſire to go thus gariſhly: If I have to cover my body and keep me warm, it contents me. The good man hearing his Wife ſay ſo, doth even leap for joy, thinking all her words Goſpel, and therefore preſently he ſets the taylor a work, willing him to diſpatch out of hand, that his wife may be brave ſo ſoon as may be. She having thus obtained her purpoſe, doth inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly triumph for very joy, howſoever outwardly ſhe doth diſſemble, And whereas before ſhe vaunted, that ſhe could find in her heart to
<pb facs="tcp:42603:5"/>keep always within doors, ſhe will be ſure now every good day to go abroad, and at each feaſt and Goſsips meeting to be a continual gueſt, that all may ſee her bravery, and how well ſhe doth become it, for which cauſe ſhe alſo comes every Sunday daily to the Church, that there ſhe may ſee and be ſeen, which her Husband thinks ſhe doth of meer devotion. But in the mean while the time runs on, and the day comes wherein the poor man muſt pay his Creditors, which being unable to do, he is at length arreſted, and after due proceeding in Law, he hath an Execution ſerved upon him, or his pawn is forfeited, and by either of both he is almoſt utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done. Then muſt his fine wife of force veil her peacocks plumes, and fall again to her old byas, keeping her houſe againſt her will, becauſe ſhe could not be furniſht with gay attire according to her mind. But God knoweth in what miſery the ſilly man doth live, being daily vexed with her brawling and ſcolding, exclaiming againſt him, that all the houſe doth ring thereof, and in this ſort ſhe begins her vagaries: Now curſed be the day that ever I ſaw thy face, and a ſhame take them that brought me firſt acquainted with thee: I would to God I had either died in my cradle. or gone to my grave when I went to be married with thee. Was ever woman of my degree and birth brought to this beggery? or any of my bringing up kept thus baſely and brought to this ſhame? I which little knew what labour meant, muſt now toyl and tend the houſe as a drudge having never a coat to my back, or ſcant handſome hoſe to my legs, and yet all little enough, whereas, I wis, I might have had twenty good marriages, in the meaneſt of which I ſhould have lived at eaſe and pleaſure, without being put to any pain, or ſuffering any penury. Wretch that I am, why do I live? Now would to God I were in my grave already, for I am weary of the World, weary of my life, and weary of all. Thus doth ſhe daily complain, and lay all the fault of her fall on him which leaſt deſerved it, nothing remembring her own pride, in coveting things above their eſtate or ability, her miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>government, and daily gadding with her Goſsips to Banquets and Bridals, when ſhe ſhould have lookt to her houſe and followed her own buſineſs at home. And his folly is alſo ſuch, that being blinded with dotage, (through too much loving her,) cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that ſhe is the cauſe of all this evil, of all the cares, griefs,
<pb facs="tcp:42603:6"/>and thoughts, which perplex and torture him, and yet nothing cuts him ſo much as this, to ſee her ſo fumiſh and unquiet, whom if he can any time ſomwhat pacifie, then is his heart ſomewhat at reſt. Thus doth the ſilly wretch roſs and turmoyle himſelf in Lobs pound, wrapt in a kind of pleaſing woe, out of the which he hath neither power nor will to winde himſelf: but therein doth conſume the remnant of his languiſhing life, and miſerably end his days.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. The humour of a woman pranked up in brave apparel.</head>
               <p>THe nature of a woman inclined to another kind of humour (which is this) when the wife ſeeing her ſelf bravely apparel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and that ſhe is therewith fair and comely, (or if ſhe be not) yet thinking her ſelf ſo (as women are naturally given to ſooth them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) ſhe doth, as I ſaid before, haunt after feaſts and ſolemn mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, wherewith her husband perhaps is not very well pleaſed: which ſhe perceiving, the more to bleer his eyes, ſhe takes with her ſome kinſwoman, or Goſsip, or poſsibly ſome luſty Gallant, of whom ſhe claims kinred, though in very deed there be no ſuch matter, but onely a ſmooth colour to deceive her husband: And perchance to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce him the ſooner to believe it, her mother (which is privy to the match) will not ſtick to ſay and ſwear it is ſo: Yet ſometime the husband to prevent his wives gadding, will feign ſome left; as want of horſes or other like hinderances: then preſently the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſip or Kinſwoman (of whom before I ſpake) will thus ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſault him.</p>
               <p>Believe me Goſsip, I have as little pleaſure as who hath leaſt in going abroad, for I wis I had not ſo much buſineſs to do this xii moneths as I have at this inſtant: yet ſhould I not go to this wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, being ſo kindly bidden, I know the young Bride would take it in very ill part. Yea and (I may ſay to you) ſo would our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, and other our friends which will be there, who would verily imagine, we keep away for ſome other cauſe: and were it not for this I proteſt I would not ſtir out of doors, neither would my Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin your wife have any deſire to go thither: thus much I can truly witneſs that I never knew any woman take leſs delight in ſuch things than your wife; or which being abroad, will make more haſte to be at home again.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:42603:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> The ſilly man her Husband, being vanquiſhed by theſe words, and no longer able to deny their requeſt, demands only what other wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men do appoint to go, and who ſhall man them? Marry Sir: (ſaith ſhe) that ſhall my Couſin <hi>H.</hi> And beſides your wife and I, there goes my Kinſwoman <hi>T.</hi> and her Mother, Miſtreſs <hi>H.</hi> and her Aunt: my Vncle <hi>T.</hi> &amp; his Brother, to be met with both their wives, Miſtreſs <hi>C.</hi> my next neighbour: and to conclude, all the women of account in this ſtreet: (I dare boldly ſay) that honeſter Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany there cannot be, though it were to convey a Kings Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>Now it oft chanced that this ſmooth tongued Oratrix who pleads thus queintly with womans art, muſt have for her pains a Gown cloth, a Iewel, or ſome other recompence, if ſhe prevail with the good man, and cunningly play her part. He after ſome pauſe (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) will reply in this ſort: Goſsip, I confeſs it is very good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany but my wife hath now great buſineſs at home, and beſides ſhe uſeth to go very much abroad, yet for this time I am content ſhe ſhall go. But I pray you Dame (quoth he) be at home betimes. His wife ſeeing that her goſſip had gotten leave makes as if ſhe cares not for going forth, ſaying: By my faith man I have ſomething elſe to do, than to go a Bridal at this preſent: what? we have a great houſhold, and rude ſervants (God wot) whoſe idleneſs is ſuch, that they will not do any thing, if a bodies back be turn'd: for it is an old Proverb: <hi>(When the Cat is away the Mouſe will play.)</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Goſsip hold you content, we muſt not be altogether careleſs nor ſet ſo much by our pleaſure to neglect our profit: And therefore hold me excuſed, for I cannot now be ſpared nor I will not go, that is flat. Nay good goſsip (ſaith the other) ſeeing your husband hath given you leave, let us have your company this once, and if it be but for my ſake, ſuch a chance as this comes not every day. With that the good man taking the old Gyb aſide, whiſpers her thus in the ear: were it not Goſsip for the confidence I repoſe in you, I proteſt ſhe ſhould not ſtir out of doors at this time. Now as I am an honeſt woman (quoth ſhe) and of my credit Goſsip, you ſhall not need to doubt any thing.</p>
               <p>Thus to horſe they get, and away they ſpur with a merry gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop, laughing to themſelves, mocking and flouting the ſilly man for his ſimplicity: the one ſaying to the other, that he had a ſhrewd iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb facs="tcp:42603:7"/>brain, but it ſhould avail him nothing. Tuſh (ſaid the young woman) it is an old ſaying, <hi>He had need have a long ſpoon that will eat with the devil, and ſhe of a good wit that would prevent the fury of a jealous fool:</hi> and with this and the like ralk, they paſſe the time till they come to the place appointed, where they meet with luſty Gallants, who (peradventure) had at the former feaſt made the match and were come thither of purpoſe to ſtrike up the bargain. But howſoever it is, this luſty Laſſe lacks no good cheer, nor any kindneſs which they can ſhew her.</p>
               <p>Imagine now how forward ſhe will be to ſhew her beſt skill in dancing and ſinging, and how lightly ſhe will afterward eſteem her husband being thus courted and commended by a crew of luſty Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants, who ſeeing her ſo bravely attired, and graced with ſo ſweet and ſmooth a tongue, ſo ſharp a wit, ſo amiable a countenance, will each ſtrive to exceed other, in ſerving, loving, and pleaſing her: for the gallant carriage and wanton demeanour of ſo beautifull a piece, cannot chuſe but incourage a meer coward, and heat <hi>(if not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame)</hi> a frozen heart: One aſſayes her with ſugred tearms, and ſome pleaſant diſcourſe, painting forth his affection with Lovers eloquence: Another gives her a privie token, by ſtraining her ſoft hand, or treading upon her pretty foot: Another eyes her with a piercing and pitiful look, making his countenance his fancies He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauld: and perhaps the third (which is moſt likely to ſpeed) beſtows upon her a gold Ring, a Diamond, a Ruby or ſome ſuch like coſtly toy: By all which aforeſaid tokens, ſhe may well conceive their meanings, (if ſhe have any conceit at all;) and ſometimes it ſo falls out, that they fall in where they ſhould not: and ſhe ſtepping ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what aſide, doth ſo ſhrewdly ſtrain her honeſty, that hardly or never the grief can be cured. But to proceed this over-gorgeous wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his wife, drings the poor man behind hand, and doth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all cauſe a greater inconvenience; for in the end by one means or other, either through her too much boldneſs, or her Lovers-want of warineſs, the matter at length comes to light, whereof ſome friend or kinſman gives him notice.</p>
               <p>He being tickled by this bad report, thereupon ſearching further, finds it true, or gathers more likelihood of ſuſpition, &amp; that preſently infects his thoughts with jealouſie, into which mad tormenting humour, no wiſe man will ever fall: for it is an evil both extreme
<pb facs="tcp:42603:7"/>and endleſs, eſpecially (if it be juſtly conceived) upon the wives known leadneſs, for then there is no hope of curing. She on the other ſide ſeeing this, and receiving for her looſe life many bitter ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, doth cloſely keep on her old courſe, but now more for ſpight than pleaſure; for it is in vain to think that ſhe will reclaim her ſelf. And if he (hoping by conſtraint to make her honeſt) fall to beating her, (though he uſe never ſo much ſeverity) he ſhall but kindle ſo much more the fire of that lewd love, which ſhe bears unto others: Hereon follows a heap of miſchiefs; he grows careleſs of his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, letting all things run to ruine: ſhe on the other ſide becomes ſhameleſs, converting into deadly hate the love that ſhe ſhould bear him. Iudge now what a purgatory of perplexities the poor man doth live in: and yet for all this he is ſo beſotted, that he ſeems to take great pleaſure in his pains, and to be ſo far in love with Lobs pound, that were he not already in, yet he would make all haſte poſſible to be poſſeſſed of the place, there to conſume the reſidue of his life, and miſerably end his days.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. The humour of a woman lying in Child bed.</head>
               <p>THere is another humour incident to a woman, when her husband ſees her belly to grow big (though peradventure by the help of ſome other friend) yet he perſwades himſelf it is a work of his own framing: and this breeds him new cares and troubles, for then muſt he trot up and down day and night, far and near, to get with great coſt that his wife longs for? if ſhe let fall but a pin, he is diligent to take it up, leſt ſhe by ſtooping ſhould hurt her ſelf; She on the other ſide is ſo hard to pleaſe, that it is a great hap when he fits her humour, in bringing home that which likes her. though he ſpare no pains nor coſt to get it. And oft times through eaſe and plenty ſhe grows ſo queaſie ſtomacht, that ſhe can brook no common meats, but long for ſtrange and rare things, which whether they be to be had or no, yet ſhe muſt have them, there is no remedy. She muſt have Cherries, though for a pound he pay ten ſhillings, or green Peſcods at four nobles a peck: yea, he muſt take a horſe and ride into the Countrey, to get her green Codlings, when they are ſcarce ſo big as a ſcotch button. In this trouble and vexation of mind and body, lives the ſilly man for ſix or ſeven mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, all which time his wife doth nothing but complain, and he
<pb facs="tcp:42603:8"/>poor ſoul takes all the care, riſing early, going late to bed, and to be ſhort, is fain to play both the husband and the huswife. But when the time draws near of her lying down, then muſt he trudge to get Goſsips, ſuch as ſhe will appoint, or elſe all the fat's in the fire. Conſider then what coſt and trouble it will be to him, to have all things fine againſt the Chriſtning day, what ſtore of Sugar, Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, Comphets and Caraways, Marmalet, and Marchpane, with all kind of ſweet ſuckets and ſuperfluous banquetting ſtuff, with a hundred other odd and needleſs trifles, which at that time muſt fill the pockets of dainty dames: Besides the charge of the Midwife, she muſt have her nurſe to attend and keep her, who muſt make for her warm broths, and coſtly cawdels, enough both for her ſelf and her miſtreſs; being of the mind to fare no worſe than ſhe: If her miſtreſs be fed with partridge, plover, woodcocks, quails, or any ſuch like, the nurſe muſt be partner with her in all theſe dainties: neither yet will that ſuffice, but during the whole month ſhe privily pilfers away the ſugar, the nutmegs and ginger, with all other ſpices that comes under her keeping, putting the poor man to ſuch expence, that in a whole year he can ſcarcely recover that one moneths charges. Then every day after her lying down, will ſundry dames viſit her, which are her neighbors, her kinſwomen, and other her ſpecial acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, whom the good man muſt welcome with all cheerfulneſs, and be ſure there be ſome dainties in ſtore to ſet before them: where they about ſome three or four hours (or poſsibly half a day) will ſit chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with the Childwife. And by that time the cups of wine have merrily trold about, and half a dozen times moiſtned their lips with the ſweet juyce of the purple grape: They begin thus one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to diſcourſe; Good Lord neighbor, I marvel how our Goſsip <hi>Frees</hi> doth, I have no ſeen the good ſoul this many a day.</p>
               <p>Oh God help her, quoth another, for ſhe hath her hands full of work, and her heart full of heavineſs: While ſhe drudges all the week at home, her husband like an unthrift never leaves running abroad to the Tennis court, and dicing houſes, ſpending all that ever he hath in ſuch lewd ſort: yea, and if that were the worſt it is well: but hear you Goſsip, there is another matter ſpoils all, he cares no more for his wife, than for a dog, but keeps queanes even under her noſe: Ieſu faith another, who would think he were ſuch a man, he behaves himſelf to orderly and civilly to all mens ſights:
<pb facs="tcp:42603:8"/>Tuſh, hold your peace Goſsip (ſaith the other) it is commonly ſeen, the ſtill ſow eats up all the draff, he carries a ſooth countenance, but a corrupt conſcience: That I know <hi>F.</hi> well enough, I will not ſay he loves miſtreſs <hi>G.</hi> go too Goſsip, I drink to you. Yea (and ſaith another) there goes foul lies if <hi>G.</hi> himſelf loves not his maid <hi>N.</hi> I can tell you their mouths will not be ſtopt with a buſhel of wheat that ſpeak it. Then the third fetching a great ſigh, ſaying, by my troth ſuch another bold Bettreſs have I at home: for never give me credit Goſsip, if I took her not the other day in cloſe confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with her Maſter; but I think I beſwadld my maid in ſuch ſort, that ſhe will have ſmall lift to do ſo again. Nay Goſsip (ſaith another) had it been to mee, that ſhould not have ſerved her turn, but I would have turned the quean out of doors to pick a Sallet, for wot you what Goſsip? It is ill ſetting fire and flax together: but I pray you tell me one thing, when ſaw you our friend Miſtreſs <hi>C.</hi> Now in good ſooth ſhe is a kind creature, and a very gentle Peat: I promiſe you I ſaw her not ſince you and I drank a pint of Wine with her in the fiſh market. O Goſsip (ſaith another) there is a great change ſince that time, for they have been fain to pawn all that ever they have, and yet God knows her husband lies in priſon. O the paſſion of my heart (ſaith another) is all their great and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhew come to nothing? good Lord what a world is this? Why Goſsip (ſaith another) it was never like to be otherwiſe, for they loved ever to go fine, and fair daintily, and by my faith Goſſip, this is not a world for thoſe matters, and thereupon I drink to you. This is commonly their communication, where they find chear according to their choyce. But if it happen contrary, that they find not things in ſuch plenty and good order as they would wiſh, then one or other of them will talk to this effect: Truſt me goſsip, I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell much and ſo do all our other friends, that your Husband is not aſhamed to make ſo ſmall account of you, and this your ſweet child if he be ſuch a niggard at the firſt, what will he be by that time he hath five or ſix? it doth well appear he bears but little love to you whereas your vouchſafing to match with him hath done him more credit than ever had any of his kindred. Before God, ſaith ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I had rather ſee my husbands eyes our then he ſhould ſerve me ſo: therefore if you be wiſe uſe him not to it: neither in this ſort let him tread you under foot: I tell you it is a foul ſhame for him, and
<pb facs="tcp:42603:9"/>you may be well aſſured ſith he begins thus y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hereafter he will uſe you in the ſame order, if not worſe. In good ſooth ſaith the third it ſeems very ſtrange to me that a wiſe woman, and one of ſuch parentage as you are, who as all men konws, is by blood far his better, can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to be thus uſed by a baſe companion. Blame us not to ſpeak, good Goſsip, for I proteſt the wrong that he doth you doth likewiſe touch us, and all other good women that are in your caſe.</p>
               <p>This Child wife hearing all this, begins to weep, ſaying: Alas Goſſip, I know not what to do or how to pleaſe him, he is ſo divers and wayward a man, and beſides he thinks all too much that is ſpent. Goſsip he is (ſaid one) a bad and a naughty man, and ſo it is well ſeen by your uſage. All my Goſſips here can tell, that when I was married to my husband, every one ſaid that he was ſo haſty and hard to pleaſe, that he would kill me with grief: and indeed I may ſay to you, I found him crabbed enough: for he began to take upon him mightily, and thought to have wrought wonders, yet I have uſed ſuch means that I have tamed my young maſter, and have at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent brought him to that paſſe, that I dare ſwear he had rather loſe one of his joints than wrangle with me: I will not deny but once or twice he beat me ſhrewdly, which I, God wot, being young and tender, took in grievous part, but what he got by it let my Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſip <hi>T.</hi> report, who is yet a woman living, and can tell the whole ſtory: to whom my good man within a while after ſaid, that I was paſt remedy. and that he might ſooner kill me: than do any good by beating me, (and by theſe ten bones ſo he ſhall) but in the end I brought the matter ſo about, that I got the bridle into my own hands, ſo that I may now ſay I do what I lift: for be it right or wrong, if I ſay it he will not gain ſay it; for by this Gold on my finger, let him do what he can, I will be ſure to have the laſt word; ſo that in very deed, if that women be made underlings by their husbands, the fault is their own: For there is not any man alive (be he never ſo churliſh) but his wife may make him quiet and gentle enough, if ſhe have any wit. And therefore your good man ſerves you but well enough, ſith you will take it ſo.</p>
               <p>Believe me Goſſip (ſaith another) were I in your caſe, I would give him ſuch welcome at his coming home, and ring ſuch a peale of bad words in his ears, that he ſhould have ſmall joy to ſtay the hearing.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:42603:9"/>
               <p> Thus is the poor man handled behind his back, whiles they make no ſpare to help away with his good wine and ſugar (which he hath prepared,) whom they for his kindneſs thus ingratefully requite: yea, and now and then having their brains well heated, they will not ſtick to taunt him to his face: accuſing him of little love and great unkindneſs to his wife.</p>
               <p>Now it doth many times ſo chance, that he having been forth to provide ſuch meats as ſhe would have, he cometh home (perhaps at midnight) and before he ſitteth down to reſt himſelf, hath a very earneſt deſire to know how his wife doth, and perchance being loth to lie abroad, becauſe of expence travels the later, that he may reach to his own houſe where (when he is once come) he asketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bermaid, or elſe the Nurſe, how his wife doth: they having their errand before given them by their Miſtreſs, anſwers, ſhe is very ill at eaſe, and that ſince his departure ſhe taſted not one bit of meat: but that towards y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> evening ſhe began to be a little better, all which be meer lyes. But the poor man bearing theſe words, grieves not a little, though he be all to be moyld, weary and wet, having gone a long journey through a bad and filthy way upon ſome ill paced trot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Iade, and may be is faſting too: yet will he neither eat nor drink, (nor ſo much as once ſit down) till he have ſeen his Wife, Then the idle pratling Nurſe, which is not to learn to exploit ſuch a piece of ſervice, begins to look very heavily, and to ſigh inwardly as though her Miſtreſs had been that day at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> point of death; which he ſeeing, was the more earneſt to viſit his wife: whom at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the Chamber, he hears lye groaning to her ſelf, and coming to the bed ſide, kindly ſits down by her, ſaying, how now my ſweet heart, how doſt thou? Ah husband (quoth ſhe) I am very ill, nor was I ever ſo ſick in my life, as I have been this day. Alas good ſoul (ſaith he) I am the more ſory to hear it. I pray thee tell me where lies thy pain? Ah husband (quoth ſhe) you know I have been weak a long time, and not able to eat any thing. But Wife (quoth he) why did you not cauſe the Nurſe to boyl you a Capon, and make a meſs of good broth for you? So ſhe did (ſaid his wife) as well as ſhe could, but it did not like me God wot, and by that means I have eaten nothing, ſince the broth which your ſelf made me: Oh me thought that was excellent good.</p>
               <p>Marry Wife (ſaith he) I will preſently make you ſome more of
<pb facs="tcp:42603:10"/>the ſame, and you ſhall eat it for my ſake. With all my heart good husband (ſaith ſhe) and I ſhall think my ſelf highly beholden unto you. Then trudgeth he into the Kitchin, there playes he the Cook, burning and brotling himſelf over the fire, having his eyes ready to be put out with ſmoak while he is buſie in making the broth: what time he chides with his maids, calling them beaſts and baggages, that knows not how to do any thing: not ſo much as make a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle broth for a ſick body, but he muſt bee fain to do it himſelf. Then comes down Miſtreſs Nurſe as fine as a farthing fiddle, in her petticoat and girtle, having a white waſtcoat, with a flaunting cambrick Ruffe about her neck; who like a Doctreſs in faculty, comes thus upon him. Good Lord ſir, what pains you take, here is no body can pleaſe our Miſtreſs but your ſelf: I will aſſure you (on my credit) that I do what I can, yet for my life, I cannot any way content her. Moreover here came in miſtreſs Cot, and miſtreſs <hi>Cen.</hi> who did both of them what they could to have your Wife eat ſomthing: Nevertheleſs, all they did could not make her taſte one ſpoonful of any thing all this live-long day: I know not what ſhe ayls: I have kept many women in my time, both of worſhip, and credit, (ſimple though I ſtand here) but I never knew any ſo weak as ſhe is: I, I (quoth he) you are a company of cunning Cooks, that cannot make a little broth as it ſhould be. And by this time the broth being ready, he brings it ſtraight to his wife, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting her with many kind words, praying her to eat for his ſake, or taſte a ſpoonful or twain, which ſhe doth, commending it to the Heavens, affirming alſo that the broth which the others made had no good taſte in the world, and was nothing worth. The good man hereof being not a little proud, bids them make a good fire in his wives chamber, charging them to tend her well. And having given this direction, he gets himſelf to ſupper with ſome cold meat ſet before him, ſuch as the Goſsips left, or his Nurſe could ſpare, and having this ſhort pittance he goes to hed full of care.</p>
               <p>The next morning he gets him up betimes, and comes very kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to know how his wife doth, who preſently pops him in the mouth with a ſmooth lye: ſaying that all night ſhe could take no reſt till it grew towards the morning, and then ſhe began to feel a little more eaſe, when God knows ſhe never ſlept more ſoundly in all her life. Well wife, (ſaid the good man) you muſt remember that this night
<pb facs="tcp:42603:10"/>is our goſsips ſupper, and they will come hither with many other of our friends, therefore we muſt provide ſome good thing for them, eſpecially becauſe it is your upſitting and a fortnight at leaſt ſince you were brought to bed: but good wife let us go as near to the World as we may, ſeeing that our great charge doth every day in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and mony was never ſo ill to come by.</p>
               <p>She hearing him ſay ſo, begins to pout, ſaying; would for my part I had died in travel, and my poor infant been ſtrangled in the birth, ſo ſhould you not be troubled with us at all, nor have cauſe to repine ſo much at our ſpending: I am ſure there is never a woman in the world, that in my caſe hath worſe keeping or is leſs charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, yet let me pinch and ſpare, and do what I can all is thought too much that I have: Truſt me I care not a ſtraw whether you provide me any thing or no, although the ſorrow be mine, the ſhame will be yours, as yeſterday for example: I am ſure here came in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a dozen of our neighbours and friends of meer kindneſs to ſee me, and know how I did, who by their countenance and comming, did you greater credit then you deſerve: But God knows what en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment they had, having nothing in the houſe to ſet before them which made me ſo much aſhamed, that I knew not what to ſay: I tell you what, before God I may boldly ſpeak it, (for I have ſeen it) that when any one of them lies in, their very ſervants have better fare then I my ſelf have had at your hands, which they ſeeing (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt themſelves yeſterday) when they where here, did moſt cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly flout both you and me for their entertainment. I have not (as you know) lien in above fifteen days, &amp; can yet ſcant ſtand on my legs and you think the time too long till I be moyling about the houſe (to catch my bane,) as I fear I have done already. Believe me wife (quoth he) you miſtake me greatly, for no man in the world can be more kind to his wife, then I have done already. Kind to me (quoth ſhe) by the maſſe that you have with a murren: no doubt but I have had a ſweet meſſe of cheriſhing at your hands, but I ſee your drift well enough, you gape every day for my death, and I would to God it were ſo for me: the month end is half expired, and I fear the reſt will come before we be ready for it: my ſiſter <hi>S.</hi> was here no longer ago then to day, and askt if I had ever a new Goun to be Churched in, but God wot I am far enough from it, neither do I deſire it, though it be a thing which ought both by reaſon &amp; cuſtome to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:42603:11"/>
               <p> And becauſe it is your pleaſure, I will riſe to morrow what chance ſo euer befall, for the worſt is, I can but loſe my life: full well may I gather by this, how you will uſe me hereafter, and what recount you would make of me, if I had nine or ten Children, but God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid it ſhould ever come to paſs, I deſire rather to be rid of my life, and to ſhun the ſhame of the world, than long to live with ſuch an unkind churl. Now verily wife (ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good man) I muſt needs blame your impatience for growing ſo cholerick without cauſe. Without cauſe quoth ſhe?) do you think I have no juſt cauſe to complain? I will aſſure you there is never a woman of my degree, that would put up the intolerable injuries that I have done, &amp; daily do by means of your hoggiſh conditions, Well wife, ſaith the good man,<note place="margin">Fox <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>apes</note> ly as long as you liſt, and riſe when you will, but I pray you tel me how this new Gown may be had which you ſo earneſtly ask for: By my faith (quoth ſhe) you ſay not well, for I ask nothing at your hands, neither would I have it though I might: I thank God I have gowns enough already, &amp; ſufficient to ſerve my turn, &amp; you know I take no delight in gariſh attire, for I am paſt a girle, but it makes me ſmile to ſee what a ſhew of kindneſs you would fain make: Fie on thee diſſembler, you can cog and flatter as well as any man in this Town, and full little think they that ſee you abroad, what a Devil you are at home: for what with your crooked qualities with toyling, moyling, carking and caring, and being beſide broken with Child bearing, my countenance is quite changed, ſo that I look already as withered,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> as the bark of an Elder bough: There is my couſin, T. T. who when I was a little girle, was at a womans eſtate, and in the end married maſter H. with whom ſhe leads a Ladies life looking ſo young and luſty, that I may ſeem to be her mother, I, I, ſuch is the difference betwixt a kind and an uncourteous husband: and who knows not but he was a ſuter to me &amp; made many a jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dey to my fathers houſe for my ſake, and would ſo fain have had me, that while I was to marry, he would not match himſelf with any? but ſo much was I bewitch'd, that after I had once ſeen you, I would not have changed for the beſt Lord in the Land, and this I have in recompence of my love and loyalty: Go to wife (ſaith he) I pray you leave theſe laviſh ſpeeches, and let us all call to mind where we may beſt take up cloth for your gown: for you ſee, ſuch is our weak eſtate, that if we ſhould raſhly lay out that little
<pb facs="tcp:42603:11"/>money which is in the houſe, we might poſsibly be unprovided for all other neceſſaries: therefore whatſoever ſhould chance hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it is beſt to keep ſomething againſt a rainy day: And again, you know within theſe eight or nine days, I have five pound to pay to maſter <hi>P.</hi> which muſt be done, there is no ſhift, otherwiſe I am like to ſuſtain treble dammage. Tuſh (quoth ſhe) what talke you to me of theſe matters? alas I ask you nothing, I would to God I were once rid of this trouble: I pray you let me take ſome reſt, for my head akes (God help me) as it ſhould go in pieces, I wis you feel not my pain, and you take little care for my grief: Therefore I pray you ſend my goſſips word that they may not come, for I feel my ſelf very ill at eaſe. Not ſo (quoth he) I will never break cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, nor ſo much as gain-ſay their courteous offer, they ſhall come ſure, and be entertained in the beſt manner I may. Wel (quoth ſhe) I would to God you would leave me, that I might take a little reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and then do what you liſt: Vpon theſe ſpeeches the Nurſe ſtraight ſteps in, and rounds her maſter in the ear: I pray you Sir do not force her to many words, for it makes her head light, and doth great harm to a woman in her caſe, eſpecially her brains being ſo light for want of ſleep: and beſides ſhe is, God knows, a woman of a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and choice complexion, and with that ſhe draws the Curtains about the Bed: Thus is the poor man held in ſuſpence, till the next day that the Goſſips come, who will play their parts ſo kindly, and gall him to the quick with their quibs and taunts, that his courage will be wholly quail'd, and be ready (if they ſhould bid him, like the Prodigall Child, even to eat draffe with the hogs,) rather than he would diſpleaſe them. But to proceed, he in the mean while is double diligent, to provide all things againſt their coming, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his ability, and by reaſon of his wives words, he buyes more meat, and prepares a great deal better cheer than he thought to have done. At their coming, he is ready to welcome them with his cap in hand, and all the kindneſs that may be ſhewed. Then doth he trudge bare headed up and down the houſe, with a chearful counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, like a good Aſſe fit to bear the burthen: he brings the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſips up to his wife, and coming firſt to her himſelf, he tells her of their coming. I wis (quoth ſhe) I had rather they had kept at home, and ſo they would too, if they knew how little pleaſure I took in their coming. Nay I pray you wife (ſaith he) give them good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
<pb facs="tcp:42603:12"/>ſeeing they become for good will: with this they enter, and after mutual greetings, with much goſsips ceremonies, down they ſit and there ſpend the whole day in breaking their faſts, dining and in making an afternoons repaſt: beſides their petty ſuppings at her beds-ſide, and at the cradle, where they diſcharge their parts ſo well in helping him away with his good wine and ſugar, that the poor man comming oft to chear them, doth well perceive it, and grieves inwardly thereat, howſoever, he covers his diſcontent with a merry countenance. But they not caring how the game goes, take their peniworths of that chear which is before them, never asking how it comes there, and ſo they merrily paſs the time away, prattling, and talking of many good matters. Afterwards the poor man trots up and down anew to get his wife the foreſaid gown, &amp; all other things thereto ſuitable, whereby he ſets himſelf ſoundly in debt: ſometimes he is troubled with the childs brawling, ſometimes he is brawl'd at by the nurſe: then his wife complains that ſhe was never well ſince ſhe was brought to bed, then muſt he caſt his cares anew, deviſing by what means to diſcharge his debts, and leſſen his expences: then reſolves he to diminiſh his own port, and augment his wives bravery, he will go all the year in one ſuit, and make two pair of ſhwes ſerve him in a twelve month, keeping one pair for holydays, another for working dayes, and one hat in three or four years. Thus according to his own raſh deſire, he is up to the ears in Lobs pound, and for all the woe and wretchedneſs that he hath felt, hee would not yet be out again, but doth then willingly conſume himſelf in continuall care, ſorrow and trouble, til death doth ſet him free.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. The humour of a woman that hath a charge of children.</head>
               <p>THe next humour that is by nature incident to a woman, is when the husband hath been married nine or ten years, hath five or ſix childen,<note place="margin">Being ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with ſcolding, as a hack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Jade with tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</note> hath paſſed many evil dayes, unquiet nights, and troubles aforeſaid, hath his luſty youthfulneſs ſpent ſo that it is now high time for him to repent: But ſuch is his groſs folly that be cannot, and ſuch is his dulneſs through the continual vexations, which have tamed and wearied him, that he cares not whatſoever his wife ſaith or doth, but is hardned like an old Aſs, which being uſed to the whip, will not once mend his pace, be he laſhed never ſo
<pb facs="tcp:42603:12"/>much: The poor man ſeeth two or three of his daughters marriage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, which is ſoon known by their wanton tricks, their playing, dancing, and other youthful toys, but he keeps them back, having perhaps ſmall commings in, to keep, maintain and furniſh them as they look for, with gowns, kirtles, linnen, and other ornaments, as they ſhould bee for three cauſes. Firſt, that they may be the ſooner ſued unto by luſty gallants: Secondly, becauſe his denying here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhould nothing avail: for his wife which knows her daughters humours by her own, when ſhe was of the like years, will ſee that they ſhall want nothing. Thirdly they peradventure, bearing right womens minds, if their Father keeps them ſhort, will find ſome other friends that ſhall offer it them. The poor man being thus perplexed on all ſides by reaſon of the exceſsive charges which he muſt be at, will (as it is likely) be but honeſtly attired himſelf, not caring how he goes ſo he may but rub out, be it never ſo barely, and would be glad to ſcape ſo: But as the fiſh in the pond, which would alſo think himſelf well, though wanting former liverty, if he might be ſuffered to continue, is cut off before his time: So is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe this poor man ſerved, being once plunged in the perplexing pond or rather pound of wedlock and houſe keeping: for howſoever when he conſiders the aforeſaid charges and troubles, he begins to have no joy of himſelf, and is no more moved than a tyred Iade, which forceth not for the ſpur: Yet for the furniſhing of his wife and daughters, ſo that he may have peace at home, and injoy an eaſie bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, he muſt trudge up and down early and late abut his buſineſs in that courſe of life which he profeſſeth.</p>
               <p>Sometimes he journeys thirty or forty miles off, about his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs: Another time twice ſo far to the Term or Aſsiſes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſome old matter in law, which was begun by his grandfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not yet towards an end: he puts on a pair of boots of ſeven years old, which have been cobled ſo oft that they are now a foot too ſhort for him, ſo that the top of the boot reaches no further than the calf of his leg, he hath a pair of ſpurs of the old making whereof the one wants a rowell, and the other for want of leathers, is faſtned to his foot with a point: He puts a laced coat on his back, which he hath had ſix or ſeven years, which he never wore but upon high dayes, whoſe faſhion is grown clean out of requeſt, by reaſon of new invented garments: whatſoever ſports
<pb facs="tcp:42603:13"/>or pleaſures he lights on (by the way on his journey) he takes no ioy in them becauſe his mind is altogether on his troubles at home: he fares hard by the way, as alſo his poor horſe (if he have one) his man follows him in a turn'd ſute with a ſword by his ſide, which was found under a hedge at the ſiege of <hi>Bulleine;</hi> he hath a coat on his back, which every man may know was never made for him, or he not preſent when it was cut out: for the wings on his ſhoulders come down half way his arm, &amp; his skirts as much below his waſt; To be ſhort, the poor man goes every way as near as may be, for he remembers at what charges he is at home, and knows not what it will coſt him in feeing his Counſellors, Attorneys, Pettyfoggers, which will do nothing without preſent pay: he diſpatcheth his buſineſs ſpeedily, and hies him home, with ſuch haſt to avoid great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er charges, that he reſts no where by the way. And hereby it chanceth that many times he comes home at ſuch an hour, as is as neer mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as to night, and findes nothing to eat, for his wife and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants are in bed, all which he takes patiently, being now well uſed to ſuch entertainment: Surely for my part, I think that God ſends ſuch adverſity and diſtreſs to thoſe only whoſe good and mild nature he knows to be ſuch, that they will take all things in good part.</p>
               <p>But to proceed, it is very likely that the poor man is very weary, his heart heavy, by reaſon of the care and thought which he hath of his buſineſs: and it may be (he looks to be welcome to his own houſe, and there to refreſh himſelf) howſoever he forgets not his former uſage. But it falls out otherwiſe, for his wife begins to chidee whoſe words carry ſuch a ſway with the ſervants, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their maſter ſaith, they make ſmall account of it: but if their miſtreſs command any thing, it is preſently done, and her humour followed in all things, elſe muſt they pack out of ſervice; ſo that it boots not him to bid them do any thing, or rebuke them for not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it: And his poor man that hath been with him dares not like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe open his mouth to call for any victualls to comfort himſelf, or for the horſes, leſt they ſhould ſuſpect him to be of his maſters facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (who being wiſe and of a quiet mild nature) is loth to make any ſtir, or breed any diſquietneſs in the houſe, and therefore takes all in good part, and ſits down far from the fire, though hee be very cold: But his wife and children ſtand round about it, but all
<pb facs="tcp:42603:13"/>their eyes are caſt on her, who looks on her husband with an angry countenance, not caring to provide ought for his ſupper: but contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe taunts him with ſharp and ſhrewd ſpeeches, whereto for the moſt part, he anſwers not a word, but ſometimes (perhaps being ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged through hunger or wearineſe, or unkindneſs of his wife) he doth thus utter his mind. Well miſe you can look well enough to your ſelf, but as for me, I am both weary and hungry, having neither ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten nor drunk n all this day, and being beſide wet to the very skin, yet you make no eeckoning toprovide any thing for my ſupper.</p>
               <p>Ah (quoth ſhe) you do well to begin firſt, leſt I ſhould, which have moſt cauſe to ſpeak: have you not done very well (think ye) to take your man with you, and leave me no body to white the cloathe? Now before god, I have more loſs in my linnen, than you will get this twelve month: Moreover, you ſhut the Hen Kouſt door very well, did you not? When the Fox got in, and eat up four of my beſt brood Hens, as you (to your roſt will ſoon find) by the maſſe, if you live long you will be the pooreſt of all your kin. Well wife (ſaith the good man) uſe no ſuch words, I pray, God you be thanked I have enough, and more ſhall have when it pleaſeth him: and I tell you, I have good men of my kin. But quoth ſhe, I know not where they be, nor what they are worth. Well (ſaith he) they are of credit and ability too. But for all that (quoth ſhe) they do you ſmall good. As much good (ſaith he) as any of yours. As any of mine (ſaith ſhe) and that ſhe ſpake with ſuch a high note, that the houſe rung withall, ſaying. By cockes ſoul, were it not for my friends you would do but ſorrily.</p>
               <p>Well good wife (ſaith he) let us leave this talk: Nay (ſaith ſhe) if they heard what you ſaid, they would anſwer you well enough. The good man holds his peace, fearing leſt ſhe ſhould tell them, being of greater ability then he was, and beſides, becauſe he was loth that they ſhould be offended with him. Then one of the three children fals a crying, and he perhaps which his father loved beſt, threupon the mother preſently took a rod, turnd up the childs tail, and whipt him well favouredly; and the more to deſpight &amp; anger her husband than for ought elſe. The good man being therewith ſomewhat moved, wills her to leave beating the child, ſhewing by his bended brows that he was not a little angry at her doings. Now gyp with a murren (qd. ſhe) you are not troubled with them, they coſt you nothing, but it is
<pb facs="tcp:42603:14"/>I that have all the pains with them night and day. Then comes in the Nurſe with her verdict, and thus ſhe begins, ſaying O Sir, you know not what a hand ſhe hath with them &amp; we alſo that tend them. Then comes in the chamber-maid with her five egs, In good faith Sir it is a ſhame for you, that at your coming home, when all the whole houſe ſhould be glad thereof, that you ſhould contrary wiſe put it thus out of quiet: ſaith he (Is it I that make this ſtir?)</p>
               <p>Then is the whole houſhold againſt him, when he ſeeing himſelf thus baited on all ſides, (and the match ſo unequall,) gets him to bed quietly without his ſupper, all wet and dirty; or if he do ſup, he hath but thin fair: and being in bed where he ſhould take his reſt, bee is ſo diſquieted with the children, whom the nurſe and his wife do on purpoſe ſet on crying, to anger him the more, that for his life he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſleep one wink.</p>
               <p>Thus is he vexed with continual troubles, wherewith he ſeemeth to be well pleaſed, and would not though he might be free from them but doth therein ſpend his miſerable and unhappy life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. The humour of a woman that marries her inferiour by birth.</head>
               <p>A Woman inclined to another kind of humour, which is, when the husband hath been married, and hath paſſed ſo many trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, that he is wearied therewith, his luſty youthful blood grown cold: is matched with a wife of better birth then himſelf, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps younger, both which things are very dangerous, and no wiſe man ſhould ſeek his own ſpoyl, by wrapping himſelf in either of thoſe bonds, becauſe they are ſo repugnant, that it is both againſt reaſon and nature to accord them. Sometimes they have children, ſometimes they have none; yet this notwithſtanding, the wife can take no pains, yet muſt be maintained according to her degree, to the husbanda exceeding charges: for the furniſhing whereof, the poor man is forced to take extream toil and pains, and yet for all this thanks God for vouchſafing him ſo great a grace, as to be matcht with her: If now and then they grow to hot words together (as oft it happens) then preſently in upbrading and menacing ſort, ſhe tells him that her friends did not match her to him to be his drudge, and that ſhe knows well enough of what linage ſhe is come, and will
<pb facs="tcp:42603:14"/>brag withall, that when ſhe liſt to write to her friends and kinſmen, they will preſently fetch her away. Thus doth ſhe keep him in awe, and in a kind ſervitude, by telling him of them, who would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps have matcht her better, and not with him, but for ſome privy ſcape that ſhe hath had before, whereof the poor ſoul knows no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; or if perhaps he hath heard ſome inkling thereof, yet becauſe he is ſimple, the credit that he might give thereunto is quite daſht, by a contrary tale of others ſuborn'd by them, who perchance will not ſtick to ſwear that this is a ſlaunder rais'd by evil tongues, and forced maliciouſly againſt her, as the like is done againſt many other good women, whoſe good names are wronged, &amp; brought in queſtion by bad perſons on their tipling bench becauſe themſelves cannot ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their purpoſe of them: notwithſtanding, if her husband be not able to maintain her according to her mind, then will ſhe be ſure to have a friend in ſtore that ſhall offer it her, if her husband deny it, and in the end ſhe remembers that ſuch a Gentleman at ſuch a feaſt profered her a Diamond, or ſent her by a meſſenger ſome twenty or thirty crowns, which ſhe as then refuſed, but now purpoſeth to give him a kind glance to renew his affection, who conceiving ſome bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hope, and meeting ſoon after with her Chamber-maid, as ſhe is going about ſome buſineſs, calls to her, ſaying: Siſter I would fain ſpeak with you. Sir quoth ſhe ſay what you pleaſe. You know (quoth he) that I have long loved your Miſtreſs without obtaining any favour: but tell me I pray you, did ſhe never ſpeak of me in your hearing? In faith ſir (ſaith he) never but well: I dare ſwear ſhe wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes you no harm. Before God ſiſter, ſaith the Gentleman, if you will ſhew me ſome kindneſs herein, and do my commendations to your miſtreſs, aſſuring her of my love and loyalty, it ſhould be worth a new gown unto you, mean while take this in earneſt; with that he offers her a piece gold; ſhe then making a low curſie, ſaith Sir, I thank you for your good will, but will not take it; By my faith ſaith he, but you ſhall, and with that he forceth it on her; adding theſe words: I pray you let me hear from you to morrow morning. She being glad of ſuch a booty hies her home, and tels her miſtreſs how ſhe met with a gentleman that was in a paſſing good vein, &amp; to be ſhort after ſome queſtions uſed by her miſtreſs, it appears to be the very ſame man whom ſhe would fain entrap. I tell thee, ſaith ſhe to her maid, if he be as kind as he is proper, he were worthy to be any wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans
<pb facs="tcp:42603:15"/>love. Believe me miſtreſs (ſaith the maid) his very countenance ſhews that he is kind, it ſeemes that he was only made for love, and withall he is wealthy, and thereby able to maintain her beauty and her perſon in bravery whom he affects. By this light (ſaith the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs) I can get nothing of my husband. The more unwiſe you (ſaith the maid) to be uſed ſo. Alas quoth ſhe what ſhall I do? I have had him ſo long, that I cannot now ſet my heart on any other. Tuſh (quoth the maid) it a folly of any woman to ſet her heart ſo on any man, for you know they care not how they uſe us when they are once lords over us. Beſide, your husband, though he would yet he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not maintain and keep you according to your degree: but he of whom I ſpeak will furniſh and maintain you gallantly, what garments ſoeuer he will have: and what colour and faſhion ſoever you like beſt you ſhall preſently have it, ſo that there wants nothing elſe, ſave on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a quaint excuſe to my Maſter, making him believe you had it by ſome other means. By my troth quoth her miſtreſs, I know not what to ſay. Well Miſtreſs (ſaith the maid) adviſe you well, I have promiſt to give him an anſwer to morrow morning. Alas (ſaith the other,) how ſhall we do? Tuſh miſtreſs, anſwers the maid, let me alone: As I go to morrow to the market, I am ſure he will watch to meet with mee, that he may know what news: then I will tell him that you will not agree to his deſire for fear of diſcredit, this will give him a little hope and ſo we ſhall fall into further talk, and I doubt not but to handle the matter well enough. According to promiſe next morning to market ſhe hies, ſomewhat more early then ſhe was wont, and by the way ſhe meets with this luſty gallant, who had waited for her at leaſt three hours: he hath no ſooner ſpied her, but he preſently makes towards her, and at her coming thus ſalutes her: Siſter, good morrow, what news I pray, and how doth your fair Miſtreſs? In faith Sir, (ſaith ſhe) ſhe is at home very pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive and out of patience; I think that never any woman had ſuch a froward husband. Ah villain (ſaith hee) the Devil take him. Amen (ſaith the maid) for both my miſtreſs and all the ſervants are weary with tarrying with him, Out on him ſlave (ſaith he) but I pray you tell me what anſwer gave your Miſtreſs touching my ſuit? In faith (quoth ſhee) I ſpake unto her, but ſhe would not agree thereunto, for ſhe is wonderfully afraid to purchaſe her ſelf diſcredit, and is beſides plagued with ſuch a froward and ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
<pb facs="tcp:42603:15"/>husband, and although ſhe were never ſo willing, yet could ſhe not, being continually watcht by him, his mother and brethren: I think on my conſcience, unleſs that it were that ſhe ſpake to you the other day, the poor woman talkt not with any man theſe four months; yet ſhe ſpeaks very often of you, and I am well aſſured that if ſhe would bend her mind to love, ſhe would chuſe you before all men in the World. He being raviſhed with theſe words, replyes thus, Sweet ſiſter, I pray you be my friend here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and I will alwayes reſt at your command. In good faith (ſaith ſhe) I have done more for you already, then ever I did for any man in my life. And think not (ſaith he) that I will be unmind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of your kindneſs, but what would you counſell me to do? In faith Sir (ſaith ſhe) I think it beſt that you ſhould ſpeak with her your ſelf, and now you have an excellent opportunity, for my maſter hath refuſed to give her a gown, whereat ſhe ſtormes not a little, you ſhall do well therefore to be to morrow at the Church, and there ſalute her, telling her boldly your deſire: you may alſo offer her what you think good, but I know ſhee will take nothing: marry ſhe will think the better of you, knowing thereby your frank and bountiful nature. Oh, (ſaith he) I would ſhe would gladly take that which I would gladly beſtow on her. Nay, anſwers the maid, I know ſhe will not, for you never knew a more honeſter woman: but I'le tell yee how ye may do it after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: Look what you purpoſe to beſtow upon her, you ſhall deliver unto me, I will do my beſt to perſwade her to take it: but I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not aſſure you that I ſhall prevail. Surely ſiſter (ſaith he) this is very good counſell, herewithall they part, and ſhe returns home, laughing to her ſelf; which her miſtreſs ſeeing, demands of her the cauſe thereof. Marry (ſaith the maid) this luſty gentleman is all on fire, to morrow he will be at Church; purpoſing there to ſpeak with you; now muſt you demean your ſelf wiſely, and make very ſtrange of it, but ſtand not off too much, leſt you diſmay him clean: as you will not wholly grant, ſo muſt you feed him with ſome hope. She having her leſſon thus taught by her maid gets her up betimes the next morning, and to the Church ſhe goes, where this amorous Gallant hath waited for her comming ever ſince four a clock. She being ſet in her Pew, makes ſhew as if ſhe were devoutly at her prayers, when (God wot) her devotion is bent to the ſervice of
<pb facs="tcp:42603:16"/>another Saint: it were worth the noting to ſee how like an image ſhe ſits: and yet for all her demureneſſe, ſhe applyes all her five ſenſes, and that full zealouſly in this new humour of religion. To be ſhort, he ſteals unto her ſneaking unto her from the belfrey unto her Pew, and being come, greetes her after the amorous order, and from greeting he falls to courting, whereto ſhe doth in no wiſe yeild conſent, neither will ſhe take ought that ſhe offers, yet anſwers him after ſuch a ſort that he doth aſſurely gather that ſhe loveth him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, and ſticks only for fear of diſcredit: whereat he is not a little jocund, and having ſpent his time to ſo good a purpoſe, he takes his leave and ſhe haſting home to her Counſellour, acquaints her what hath paſſed between them; who thereupon takes occaſion to ſay thus, Miſtreſs, I know well that now he longs to ſpeak with me, but at our meeting I will tell him that you will yeild to nothing for which I will fain my ſelf ſorry: And I will add withall, that my maſter is gon out of town, and will appoint him to come hither towards the evening, with promiſe that I will let him in, and convey him ſo ſecretly into your Chamber, that you ſhall know nothing thereof. At what time you muſt ſeem to be highly offended, and if you be wiſe, you will make him buy his pleaſure with ſome coſt, which will cauſe him to eſteem the more of you; Tell him that you will cry out, and then do you call me. By handling him thus, I can aſſure you that you ſhall get more of him, than if you had yeilded at the firſt. All this while I will have in my keeping that which he will give you, for hee hath appointed to deliver it me to morrow, and I will make him believe, that you would by no means take it. But when the matter is brought to this paſs, then will I make ſhew to offer you his gift before him, telling you that he is willing you beſtow it on you to buy you a gown cloth withall: Then muſt you chide, and ſeem to bee angry with me for receiving it, charging me to deliver it back again to him, but be ſure I will lay it up ſafe enough. Well deviſed wench (ſaith the Miſtreſs) I am content it ſhall be ſo. This plot being thus laid, the crafty wench goes preſently to find out this jolly Gallant, whoſe firſt word is, What news?</p>
               <p>Now in good faith Sir, (ſaith ſhe) the matter is no further for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, then if it were yet to begin: yet becauſe I have medled ſo far in it, I would be loth I ſhould not bring it about, for I fear that ſhe will complain of me to her husband and friends; but if I could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
<pb facs="tcp:42603:16"/>her by any means to receive your gifts, then out of queſtion the matter were diſpatcht, and in good faith I'le try once more: I have one good help, and that is this: my maſter (as I told you before) will not give her a new gown, at which unkindneſs, ſhe ſtormes mightily.</p>
               <p>The hot Lover hearing this, gives her preſently twenty Crowns for her good will, whereupon ſhe ſpeaks thus: In good faith ſir,<note place="margin">Better then two years wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and ſoon got.</note> I know not how it comes to paſs, but ſure I am, I never did ſo much for any man before, as I have done herein for you: See, ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e Sir, what danger I have put my ſelf in for your ſake; for if my Maſter ſhould have any inckling of it, I were utterly undone: yet for you I will hazard a little further: I know ſhe loves you well, as good hap is my Maſter is not now in Town, if you therefore will be about the doors toward ſix of the clock at night, I will let you in; and ſo convey you ſecretly into my Miſtreſſes Chamber, who doth ſleep very ſoundly; for you know ſhe is but young: being there I could wiſh you go to bed to her and for the reſt you need not (I truſt) any tutor: I proteſt that I know no other means for the compaſſing of this matter, perhaps it will fadge: For it is a great matter when a lover and his miſtreſs are both together naked in the dark,<note place="margin">Juſt as <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rmans</hi> lip.</note> which doth help forward a womans conceit to that which in the day time perhaps ſhe would hardly grant. Oh my ſweet friend (qd he) for this kindneſs my purſe ſhall be at thy command. To be ſhort, night comes, he is there according to promiſe, whom ſhe ſtraight conveyes into her miſtreſſes chamber, then he preſently uncloaths himſelf and ſteps ſoftly into her bed, and being once in, he begins to imbrace her, hereat ſhe (that ſeems till then aſleep) ſtarts up on a ſudden, and with a fearfull voice asks who is there? it is I ſweet Miſtreſs, ſaith he, fear nothing. Ah (qd ſhe) think you to prevail thus? No, no, and with that ſhe makes as though ſhe would riſe, and calls her maid who anſwers not a word, but alas for pitty like an undutiful ſervant leaves her at her greateſt need. She therefore (good woman) ſeeing that ſhe is forſaken, ſaith with a ſigh. Ah me, I am betrayed: then begin they a ſtout battell, hee urging his advantage, ſhe faintly reſiſting, but alas, what can a naked woman do againſt a reſolute lover? there is therefore no other remedy, but that at length (poor ſoul) being out of breath with ſtriving, ſhe muſt needs yield to the ſtronger; ſhe would fain have cryed out (God wot) had it not been for fear of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit:
<pb facs="tcp:42603:17"/>for thereby her name might have been brought in queſtion, therefore all things conſidered, ſhe doth willingly, God knows, let him ſupply her husbands place, garniſhing his Temples, for pure good will, with Acteons badge. Thus hath ſhe got a new gown, which her good man refuſed to give her; to blear whoſe eyes, and keep him from ſuſpition, ſhe gets her mother in her husbands ſight to bring home the cloath and give it her, as though it were her coſt &amp; leſt alſo he ſhould ſuſpect any thing, ſhe makes her believe ſhe bought it with the money ſhe got by ſelling old commodities which her husband knew not of: But it may be (and oft it happens ſo) that the mother is privy to the whole matter, and a furtherer thereof. After this gown ſhe muſt have another, and too or three gold imbroidered girdles, and other ſuch coſtly knacks which the husband ſeeing, will in the end ſuſpect ſomewhat, and begin to doubt of his wives hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, or ſhall perhaps receive ſome advertiſement thereof from ſome friend or kinſman: for no ſuch matter can be long kept cloſe, but in the end will by ſome means or other be made known and diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: Then falls he into a frantick vein of jealouſie, watching his Wives cloſe packing; and for the better finding it out, hee comes home on a ſudden about midnight, thinking then to diſcover all, and yet perhaps may miſſe his purpoſe. Another time coming in at un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares he ſeeth ſomething that he likes not, and then in a fury falls on railing, but be ſure that ſhe anſwers him home, not yeilding an inch unto him; for beſides the advantage of the fight; which is waged by her own truſty weapon (her tongue I mean) ſhe knowing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all that ſhe is of better birth; hits him in the taeth therewith and threatens him to tell her friends how badly he doth uſe her. To be ſhort, the poor man ſhall never have good day with her, but either with thought of her incontinency, or if he ſpeak to her, he is born down with ſcolding lyes, and deſpiſed of his own ſervants: his ſtate runs to ruine, his health decayes, his body dryes up, and wears a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with grief, he growes deſperate and careleſs. Thus is he plunged in Lobs pound, wearied in a world of diſcontents, wherein notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he takes delight, having no deſire to change his ſtate: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if he were out, and knew what would follow, yet would he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reſt till he had gotten in again, there to ſpend and end (as now he muſt) his life in grief and miſery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:42603:17"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. The humour of a woman that ſtrives to maſter her husband.</head>
               <p>THe next humour whereunto a woman is addicted, is, when the husband hath got a fair young wife, who is proper and fine in whom he takes great delight: yet perhaps ſhe is bent all together to croſſe and thwart: the man being of a kind and mild nature loving her intirely, &amp; maintains her as well as he can, notwithſtanding her fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs: it may be alſo that ſhe hath care of his credit and honeſty and doth abhor ſuch lewdneſſe as ſhe of whom we ſpeak before did uſe, yet hath ſhe nevertheleſſe an extream deſire of Soveraignty, (which is known a common fault amongſt women)and to be her husbands commander, &amp; a buſie medler in his matters: be he a Iudge, a Nobleman, or Gentleman, ſhe will take upon her to give ſentence, and anſwer ſutors, and whatſoever ſhe doth he muſt ſtand to it.</p>
               <p>This is (I ſay) a generall imperfection of women be they never ſo honeſtly, never ſo kindly uſed, and have never ſo much wealth and eaſe, to ſtrive for the breeches, and be in odde contrary humours, of purpoſe to keep her husband in continuall thought and care how to pleaſe her.</p>
               <p>He gets him up betimes in the morning, leaving her in bed to take her eaſe, while he ſtirs about the houſe and diſpatcheth his buſineſſe, look to the ſervants that they loyter not, cauſeth dinner to be made ready, the cloth to be laid, and when all things are ready, he ſends one to deſire her to come down, who brings back anſwer that ſhe is not diſpoſed to dine. Nay (ſaith he) I will never ſit down nor eat a bit till ſhe be here: So receiving his ſecond meſſage by his maid, or perhaps by one of his children; replies thus: Go tell him again that I will not dine to day. He hearing this is not yet ſatisfied but ſends likewiſe the third time, and in the end goes himſelf, and thus begins: How now, what ails you Wife, that you will eat no meat? hereto ſhe anſwers not a word. The poor man marvells to ſee her in this melancholy dump, (although perhaps ſhe hath plaid this pageant many times before) and uſeth all intreaty he may, to know of her the cauſe thereof: but in vain, for indeed there is no cauſe at all, but onely a meer mockery: Sometimes ſhe wil perſiſt ſo obſtinately in this humour, that for all the perſwaſions and kindneſſe that he can uſe, ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:42603:18"/>will not come. Sometimes it may be ſhe will, and then he muſt lead her by the hand like a Bride, and ſet her chair ready for her, mean while it is ſo long before he can get her down, that the meat is cold when it comes to the table. Being ſet, ſhe will not eat one bit, and he ſeeing that (like a kind Aſſe) will fall likewiſe: whereat ſhe ſmiles inwardly, having brought him ſo to her bow, firſt in croſsing him, then in making him faſt from dinner: wherein (to ſay the truth) ſhe hath reaſon, for what needs a woman to ſeek his favour, who doth already love her, and ſhew her all the kindneſſe that he can. Sometimes the good man riding abroad about his buſineſſe, meets with two or three of his friends, with whom perhaps he hath ſome dealings, and hath been long acquainted with them: It may be alſo that he invites them home to his houſe, as one friend will do to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſends his man before to his wife to make all things ready in the beſt ſort that ſhe can for their entertainment: the poor ſerving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man gallops in ſuch haſte, that both himſelf and his borſe is all on a ſweat, when he comes home he doth his errand to his Miſtreſs, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling her withall that the gueſts which his maſter brings are men of good account. Now by my faith (ſaith ſhe) I will not meddle in it, he thinks belike that I have nothing elſe to do, but drudge about to prepare banquets for his companions, he ſhould have come himſelf with a vengeance and why did he not? Foorſooth (ſaith the ſervant) I know not, but thus he bad me tell you. Go too (ſaith ſhe) you are a knave that meddles in more matters then you have thank for. The poor fellow hearing this holds his peace, ſhe in a fume flings up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her chamber, and which is worſe, ſends out her ſervants, ſome one way. ſome another: as for his maids, they have their leſſon taught them well enough, knowing by cuſtome how to behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to weary their Maſter: well he comes home with his afore. ſaid friends, calls preſently for ſome of his ſervants: but one of the maids makes anſwer of whom he demands whether all things be ready: In good faith Sir my Miſtreſs is very ſick, and here is no body elſe can do any thing: with that he being angry leads his friends in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Hall, or ſome other place according to his eſtate, where he finds neither fire made, nor cloath laid. Iudge then in what a taking he is, although it may be that his friends perceived by the ſending of his man, that his commandments were not of ſuch force as an act of Parliament. The good man being aſhamed, cals and gapes firſt for
<pb facs="tcp:42603:18"/>one man, then for another, and yet for all this there comes none, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be the ſcullion or ſome chare-woman, that doth uſe his houſe, whom his wife hath left there of purpoſe, becauſe ſhe knew they could ſerve to do nothing. Being herewith not a little moved, up he goes into his wives chamber, and thus he ſpeaks unto her: Gods precious woman, why have you not done as I will'd ye? Why (ſaith he) you appoint ſo many things to be done, that I know not what to do. Before God (ſaith he) and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith that he ſcratches his head, you have done me a greater diſpleaſure than you think: theſe are the deareſt friends that I have, and now here is nothing to ſet before them. Why (quoth ſhe) what would you have me to do? I wis if you caſt your care well you ſhall find that we have no need to make banquets: I would to God you were wiſer, but ſith you will needs be ſo luſty, even goe throw with it your ſelf on Gods name: for Ile not meddle with it. But what the Devil mean ye (ſaith he) to ſend all the ſervants abroad? Why (quoth ſhe) what did I know that you will need them now? yet did ſhe know it well enough, and had of purpoſe ſent them forth on ſleeveleſe errands, the more to anger and diſpight him: who ſeeing that he can prevail nothing, gives over talking to her, and gets him down in a bitter chafe: for it may be that his gueſts be of ſuch account, and he ſo much beholding unto them that he had rather have ſpent an hundred crowns than it ſhould ſo have fallen out. But ſhe cares not a whit, being well aſſured, that howſoever ſhe thwarts him, he will hold his hands, and in ſcolding ſhe knows her ſelf to be the better. To be ſhort, the poor man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vexed with ſhame and anger, runs up and down the houſe, gets as many of his ſervants together as he can: If his proviſion be but ſlender at home, he ſends preſently abroad; in the mean while he calls for a clean towel, the beſt table-cloth, and wrought napkins. But the maid anſwers him, that he can have none. Then up to his wife goes he again, and tells her that her friends do intreat her to come down and bear them company, ſhewing her what a ſhame it is and how diſcourteouſly they would take it if ſhe come not: And fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, he uſeth all the faireſt ſpeeches that he can to have her come and to welcome and entertain them for his credits ſake. Nay in faith (quoth ſhe) I will not come, they are too great ſtates for my company, and no doubt they would ſcorn a poor woman as I am. It may be ſhe will go, but in ſuch ſort, and with ſuch a countenance,
<pb facs="tcp:42603:19"/>that it had been better for him ſhe had not come at all, for his friends will ſomewhat perceive by her looks, and geſture, that howſoever they be welcome to the good man, ſhe had rather have their room than their company. But if ſhe refuſe to come (as it is the more likely) then will he ask her for the beſt towel, table-cloth and napkins. Napkins (quoth ſhe) as though thoſe that be abroad already be not good enough for greater and better men than they are: when my brother or any of my kinſmen come, which are I wis their equals in every reſpect, they can be contented to be ſerved with them: but were theſe your gueſts never ſo great, yet could I not now fulfill your requeſt though my life ſhould lie on it: for ſince morning I have loſt my keys of the great cheſt where all the linnen lies. I pray you bid the maid look for them, for in good truth I know not what I have done with them;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</note> and no marvel, for I have ſo much to do, that I know not how to beſtir my ſelf, well I wot, I have ſpoyled my ſelf with continual care and trouble.</p>
               <p>Now in good faith (quoth he) you have dreſt me fairly, but it is no matter: Before God Ile break open the Cheſt: Now ſurely then (quoth ſhe) you ſhall do a great act, I would fain ſee you do it, I would for my part you would break all the Cheſts in the houſe. The poor man hearing her in theſe tearms, knows not well what to do, but takes that which he next lights on, and therefore ſhifts as well as he can; he cauſeth his gueſts to ſit down at the table, and becauſe the beer then abroach is on tilt, and therefore not very good, he bids one of the ſervants broach a new barrell and fill ſome freſh drink but then there is neither tap nor ſpigger to be found, for his wife of purpoſe had hidden them out of the way. Towards the end of the dinner he calls for cheeſe, and fruit, but there is none in the houſe, ſo that he is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain to ſend to his neighbours for the ſame, or elſe be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſtitute: mean while his boy being at the table with the gueſts at laſt tells them how his Miſtreſs fains her ſelf ſick, becauſe ſhe is not pleaſed with their Maſters coming. Well, when bed time comes, he can get no clean ſheets nor pillowbeers, becauſe for ſooth the kepes are loſt, ſo that they muſt be content to lie in thoſe that be foul, and have been long lain in. The next morning they get them gone betimes ſeeing by the good wives countenance that they are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing welcome. By the way their lackies tell them what the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemans boy reported, whereat they laught heartily, yet find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb facs="tcp:42603:19"/>agrieved, vowing never to be his gueſt any more. The hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band alſo getting him up betimes in the morning goes preſently to his wife, and thus begins: By Ieſus wife, I muſe what you mean to uſe me thus, I know not how to live with you. Then ſhe replies, ſaying: Now God for his mercy, and I ſo troubleſome? Got wot I am every day (poor ſoul) troubled with keeping the hogs, your Geeſe, your chickens, I muſt card, I muſt ſpin, and continually keep the houſe, look to the ſervants, and never fit ſtill, but toyling up and down to ſhorten my days, and make me dye before my time, and yet I cannot have one hours reſt or quietneſs with you, but you are always brawling, and do nothing your ſelf, but ſpend and waſte your goods and mine with odde companions. What odde compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (ſaith he) as though you know not that theſe are ſuch men, as can either much further or much hinder me: It is a ſigne that you deal very well that you muſt ſtand in diſtreſs of ſuch perſons. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhe takes occaſion to rail and ſcold all the day long: the man being wearied with her wawardneſs, and age (being haſted with grief and ſorrow) doth unawares overtake him. Briefly, he is in every reſpect wretched: but ſuch is his folly, that he reckons his pains pleaſure, and would not though he might, be again at liberty, out of Lobs pound or if he would, it is now too late: for he muſt of force continue there, in care, thought, and miſery, till death make an end of him and them together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. The humour of a covetous minded Woman.</head>
               <p>THe next humour belonging to a woman is, when the Husband is matched to a modeſt civil woman, who is nothing given to that thwarting and croſſing humour whereof I ſpake before. But be ſhe good or bad, this is a general rule, many wives hold and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly believe, that their own Husbands are worſt of all others. It oft happens that when they match together, they are both young, and entertain each other with mutual delights, ſo much as may be, for a year or two or longer, till the vigour of youth grow cold. But the woman droops not ſo ſoon as the man: the reaſon whereof is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe takes no care, thought, nor grief, breaks not her ſleep, and troubles not her head as he doth but doth wholly addict her thoughts
<pb facs="tcp:42603:20"/>to pleaſure and ſolace. I deny not that when a woman is with child ſhe bides many times great pains, and is often very ill at eaſe, and at the time of her deliverance, ſhe is for the moſt part, not onely in exceeding pain, but alſo in no leſs danger of death: But all this is nothing to the husbands troubles, on whoſe hands alone doth reſt the whole charge and weight of maintaining the houſe, and diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all matters, which is oftentimes intangled ſo with controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and ſo thwarted with croſs fortune, that the poor man is tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with all vexations of mind.</p>
               <p>Being thus wearyed, and as it were worn away with continual grief, troublous cogitations, toyl and travel, he hath no mind on any other pleaſure: whereas ſhe on the other ſide is as luſty as ever ſhe was: mean while his ſtock decays, and his ſtate grows worſe and worſe: and as that diminiſheth, ſo he muſt perforce ſhorten her allowance and maintenance, which is almoſt as great a Corroſive to her, as the former: You may be well aſſured, that this change in him makes her alſo change her countenance, from mirth and cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to lowring melancholy, ſeeking occaſions of diſagreements, and uſe them in ſuch ſort, that their former love and kindneſs was not ſo great, as are now their brawls, jars, and diſcords. It doth alſo oftentimes happen, that the Woman by this means waſis and conſumes all, giving lewdly away her husbands goods, which he with great pains and cares hath gotten. The good man, he goes every way as near as he can, and wearily contains himſelf within his bounds, caſting up what his yearly revenues are, or what his gains is by his profeſſion, be it merchandiſe or other, and then what his expences be: which he finding greater then his comings in, begins to bite the lip and becomes very penſive: his wife and he being after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards private together in their chamber, he ſpeaks thereof unto her in this manner: In faith wife. I much marvel how it comes to paſs that our goods go away thus, I know not how: I am ſure I am as carefull as man can be, I cannot find in my heart to beſtow a new cloak on my ſelf, and all to ſave money. By my troth Husband (ſaith ſhe) I do as much marvel at it as you, I am ſure for mine own part, that I go as near in houſe-keeping every day as I can.</p>
               <p>To be ſhort, the poor man not doubting his wife, nor ſuſpecting her ill carriage, after long care and thought concludes, that the cauſe thereof is his own ill fortune, which keeps him down, and croſſeth
<pb facs="tcp:42603:20"/>all his actions with contrary ſucceſſe, but it may be that in proceſſe of time, ſome friend of his (being more clear fighted in the matter) perceiving all goes not will, doth privily inform him thereof, who being aſtoniſhed at his report, gets him home with a beavy counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which the wife ſeeing, and knowing her ſelf guilty, begins preſently to doubt the worſt, and perhaps gheſſeth ſhrewdly at the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor thereof; but howſoever: ſhe will take ſuch an order, that ſhe will be ſure to eſcape the brunt well enough.</p>
               <p>The good man will not preſently make any words hereof unto her, but defer it a while, and try in the mean time whether he can (of himſelfe) gather any further likelihood: for which purpoſe he will tell her, that he muſt needs ride ſome ten or twelve miles out of Town about ſome earneſt buſineſſe. Good faith husband (ſaith ſhe) I had rather you would ſend your man, and ſtay at home your ſelf. Not ſo wife (ſaith he) but I will be at home again my ſelf within theſe three or four days: Having told her this tale, he makes as though he took his journey, but doth privily lie in ambuſh in ſuch a place, where he may know whatſoever is done in the houſe: But ſhe ſmelling his drift, ſends word to her ſweet-heart, that he doe not come in any caſe, and all the time of his deſembled abſence, ſhe car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries her ſelf ſo that it gives no likelihood of ſuſpition: which the ſilly man ſeeing, comes out of his ambuſh, enters his houſe, making as if then he were returned from his journey? And whereas before he lowred now ſhews a cheerful countenance, being verily perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that his friends report is a meer lye, and that he thinks ſo much the rather, becauſe ſhe doth at his coming run to meet him, with ſuch a ſhew of love, and doth ſo imbrace and kiſſe him that it ſeems impoſſible ſo kind a creature ſhould play falſe: But long after (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in bed together) he thus ſpeaks to her:</p>
               <p>Wife, I have heard reported certain words that like me not. Good faith husband (ſaith ſhe) I know not what is the cauſe thereof: I have noted this great while that you have bin very penſive, &amp; was afraid that you had had ſome great loſſe, or that ſome of your friends had been kild, or taken by the <hi>Spaniard.</hi> No (ſaith he) that is not the matter, but a thing which grieves me more than any ſuch matter can do. Now God for his mercy (quoth ſhe) I pray you husband let me know what it is. Marry wife (ſaith he) a friend of mine told me that you kept company with <hi>R.R.</hi> the verieſt Ruſſian in all the Town,
<pb facs="tcp:42603:21"/>and a many other matters he told me of you. Here at ſhe croſſing her ſelf in token of admiration (though ſmiling inwardly) replies thus: Dear Husband, if this be all, then I pray you give over your pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiveneſſe: I would to God I were as free from all other ſins, as I am from that, then laying one hand on her head: ſhe thus proceeds: I will not ſwear any thing touching him, but I would the Devill had all this under my hand, if I ever touched any mans mouth ſaving yours or ſome of our friends and kinſmen, or ſuch at leaſt as you have commanded me. Ha, ha, is this the matter? In troth I am glad that you have told me: I had verily thought it had been ſome greater matter, but I know well enough whereupon theſe ſpeeches grew, and I would that you did likewiſe know, what moved him to ſpeak them,<note place="margin">Oh brave diſſemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler.</note> I know you would not a little marvel, becauſe he hath always profeſſed ſuch friendſhip towards you. In good faith I am nothing ſorry that he hath awaked the ſleeping dog. What mean you by that word (qd he?) Nay (quoth ſhe) be not deſirous to know it, you ſhall know it ſoon enough ſome other time. Birlady (ſaith he) I'le know it now. By my troth husband (ſaith ſhe) I was oft won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully angry when you brought him in hither, yet I forbare to ſpeak of it, becauſe I ſaw you loved him ſo well. But ſpeak now (ſaith he) and tell me what the matter is. Nay, nay (qd ſhe) it skils not greatly. Go to wife (ſaith the good man) tell me, for I will know it.<note place="margin">Almoſt as bad as <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> kiſſes.</note> Then takes ſhe him about the neck, and ſweetly kiſſing him, ſaith thus: Ah my dear Husband, what villains are theſe that would ſeem to abuſe you, whom I honour and love above all men in the world, Well Wife (ſaith he) I pray thee tell me the man that ſo miſuſeth us.<note place="margin">The devill take the lyar.</note> In troth (quoth ſhe) that vile diſſembling Traitor, that flattering tell tale, that puts that bad report in your ears, whom you eſteem ſo much: repoſing ſuch great confidence in him, he is the only man and none but he, that hath earneſtly urged me any time this two years to commit folly with him. But God (I praiſe him) hath given me grace both to refuſe him and his offers, although I were continually troubled and importuned by him: I wis, when you thought he came hither ſo often for your ſake,<note place="margin">Thus is he bor'd tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the noſe with a cuſhen.</note> it was for this cauſe for never a time that he came, but he was in hand with me to obtain his filthy deſire, till in the end I threatned to tell you of it, but I was loth to do it, fearing to breed a quarell between you, ſo long as I was ſure to keep him from doing you herein any injury: Beſide,
<pb facs="tcp:42603:21"/>I had ſtill a good hope, that he would at length give over: I wis it was no fault of his that he ſped not. Gods for my life (ſaith the good man) being in a great rage, what a treacherous villain is this? I would never have ſuſpected any ſuch matter in him, for I durſt have put my life in his hands. By this light Husband (ſaith ſhe) if ever he come more within the doors, or if ever I may know that you have any talk with him, Ile keep houſe no longer with you. Ah dear Husband, and with that ſhe clips and culs him again about the neck, ſhould I be ſo diſloyal as to abuſe you in this ſort? ſo ſweet,<note place="margin">As kind as a Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crab, ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing on a dead car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion.</note> ſo amiable, &amp; ſo kind a man, who lets me have my will in all things? God forbid I ſhould live ſo long to become a ſtrumpet now. But for Gods ſake Husband, forbid him your houſe with whom this knave hath ſlandered me withal, yet I would the Devil had me if ever he made ſuch motion to me: nevertheleſſe, by Gods grace he ſhall not come henceforth in any place where I am and with that ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to weep, and he (kind fool) doth appeaſe and comfort her, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing and ſwearing that he will do as ſhe will have him, ſave only that he will not forbid him his houſe, with whoſe company the other had charged her, and withall he vows, never to believe any more of theſe reports, nor ſo much as to harken to any ſuch tales again, notwithſtanding he ſtill feels a ſcruple of ſuſpition in his conſcience: Within a while he begins to fall at defiance with his honeſt friend, who informed him of his Wives wantonneſſe, and he ſeems to be ſo deeply beſotted with her love, that you would ſay he were tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed without inchantment, into <hi>Acteons</hi> ſhape: His charge of Houſhould ſtill increaſeth, he hath many Children, and is perplexed on every ſide; but his Wife follows her pleaſure far more than before, for though it be never ſo openly known, yet will no man tell him thereof, becauſe they know that he will not believe them, and (which is more ridiculous) he that abuſeth him moſt, ſhall be moſt welcome unto him of any. To be ſhort, age will overtake him, and perhaps poverty, from the which he will never be able to raiſe himſelf. Lo here the great good and pleaſure that he hath gotten by entring into Lobs pound, every man mocks him; ſome ſay it is pitty becauſe he is an honeſt man: others ſay, it is not a matter to be ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed for, ſith it is the common rule of ſuch. They of the better ſort will ſcorn his company. Thus lives he in pain, grief, and diſgrace. which he takes for great pleaſure, and therein will continue till death cut him off.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:42603:22"/>
               <head>CHAP, VIII. The humour of a woman that ſtill deſires to be gadding abroad.</head>
               <p>THe next humour of a woman is, when the husband hath been in Lobs pound ſome five or ſix years, part whereof he hath ſpent in ſuch pleaſure as wedlock doth at the firſt afford, but now the date of theſe delights is out, he hath perhaps ſome three or four children: but his wife is now big again, end a great deal worſe of this child than ſhe was of any other: whereat the poor man grieves not a little, who takes great pains to get her that which ſhe longs for: Well, the time of her lying down draws near, and ſhe is wonderfully out of temper: ſo that it is greatly feared that ſhe will hardly eſcape. Then falls he on his knees, and prays devoutly for his Wife, who ſoon after is brought to bed, wherefore he is not a little jocond, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſure account that God hath heard his prayers. She goſhips, kinſwomen and neighbours, come in troops to viſit and rejoyce for her ſafe delivery. She for her part wants no good cheriſhing, whereby ſhe recovers her ſtrength, and is as freſh and luſty as ever ſhe was.</p>
               <p>After her Churching, ſhe is invited by ſome of her neighbours. who alſo invites five or ſix others of her neighbours and friends, who is received and feaſted with all kindneſs; which Banquet doth perhaps coſt her Husband more than would have kept the houſe a whole fortnight: Amongſt other ſhe propounds a queſtion, &amp; makes a match to go all together to a certain Fair, which will be within ten days at ſuch a place, to the which place they ſhall have a moſt brave and pleaſant journey, by reaſon of the fair weather, for they will always conclude ſuch an agreement in ſome of the beſt ſeaſons of the year, and ſhe takes upon her to make this motion chiefly in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of her Goſſip, which was lately brought a bed, that ſhe may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her long pain and travel ſomewhat recreate and refreſh her ſelf. But ſhe anſwered her with thanks for her good will, ſaying, ſhe knows not how to get leave of her Husband. What (ſaith the other) that is the leaſt matter of a thouſand. Tuſh Goſſip (ſaith another) ſtand not upon that, we will all go and be merry, and we will have with us my Goſſip <hi>G. T.</hi> my Couſin <hi>H. S.</hi> though perhaps he be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing kind to her: But this is their ordinary phraſe, and they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take this journey, becauſe they cannot ſo well obtain their purpoſes
<pb facs="tcp:42603:22"/>at home, being too near their Husbands noſes. After this agreement, home ſhe comes with a heavy countenance: The good man asketh what ſhe aileth. Marry (quoth ſhe) the Child is very ill at eaſe, (though he were never in better health ſince he was born) his fleſh burns as though it were fire, and as the Nurſe tells me, he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed the dug theſe two days, although ſhe durſt not ſay ſo much till now. He hearing this and thinking it true, is not a little ſorry, goes preſently to ſee his Child, and weeps for pity.</p>
               <p>Well, night comes, to bed they go, and then ſhe fetching a ſigh, begins thus: Husband, I ſee you have forgotten me. How mean you that, ſaith he? Marry (quoth ſhe) do you not remember that when I was in child bed you ſaid, that if it pleaſed God that I eſcaped, I ſhould go to ſuch a Fair with my Goſſips and neighbours to make merry, and cheer up my ſelf, but now I hear you not talk of it. In troth wife (ſaith he) my head is troubled with ſo many matters, and ſuch a deal of buſineſs, that I have no leiſure to think on any thing elſe: but there is no time paſt yet, the Fair will not be this fortnight. By my troth (quoth ſhe) I ſhall not be well unleſs I go. Well wife (ſaith he) content your ſelf: for if I can by any means get ſo much money ye ſhall go. You know it is not little that we ſhall ſpend there: yea more I wis then will be my eaſe to lay out. Good Chriſt (quoth ſhe) is it now come to that? you promiſed me ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, without either ifs or auns: before God I will go, whether you will or no: for there goes my Mother, my Goſſip <hi>T.</hi> my Couſin <hi>B</hi> and my Couſin <hi>R.</hi> and his wife. If you will not let me go with them, I know not with whom you will let me go. He hearing her thus wilful, thinks it beſt for his own quietneſſe, to let her go, though he ſtrain his purſe ſomewhat the more. The time comes, he hires horſes, buyes her a new riding gown, and doth furniſh her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to her mind: peradventure there goes in their company a lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty Gallant, that will frollick it by the way on her Husbands coſt, for his purſe muſt pay for all. It may be he will go himſelf, becauſe he hath never a man, or elſe cannot ſpare him from his work. But then is the poor man notably perplexed, for ſhe will on purpoſe trouble him for every trifle more than ſhe would do to another: becauſe it doth her good to make a drudge of him; and ſo much the rather, that he may not afterwards have any deſire to go abroad with her again.</p>
               <p>Sometime her ſtirrop is too long, ſometimes too ſhort: and he
<pb facs="tcp:42603:23"/>muſt ſtill alight to make it fit: ſometimes ſhe will wear her cloak, ſometimes not, and then he muſt carry it. Then finds ſhe fault with her horſes trotting, which makes her ſick, and then ſhe will alight and walk on foot, leaving him to lead the horſes. Within a while after they come to a water, then muſt he be troubled to help her up again. Sometimes ſhe can eat nothing that is in the Inne, then muſt he (being weary all day with riding) trudge up and down all the Town, to find ſomething that will fit her ſtomach: All which notwithſtanding, ſhe will not be quiet: and not ſhe onely, but her Goſſips alſo will be bobbing and quipping him, ſaying that he is not worthy to be a womans man. But he is ſo inured to theſe janglings that he cares not for all their frivolous words.</p>
               <p>Well at length to the Fair they come, and then muſt he play the Squire in going before her, making ſo much room for them as he can, when there is any throng or preſſe of people, being very chary of his wife, leſt ſhe ſhould be hurt or annoyed by thruſting. There moyles he like a Horſe, and ſweats like a Bull, yet cannot all this pleaſe her. Some Dames of the company, which are more fluſh in crowns than her good man, beſtows money on Gold Rings, Hats, ſilk Girdles, Iewels, or ſome ſuch toyes; yea, coſtly toyes, which ſhe no ſooner ſees, but preſently ſhe is on fire; untill ſhe have the like. Then muſt he herein content her, (if he love his own eaſe) and have he money or not, ſome ſhift muſt be made to ſatisfie her humor. Well now imagine them going homewards, and think his pain and trouble no leſſe, than it was coming forth: her Horſe perhaps doth flounder much, or trots too hard, which is peradventure by reaſon of a nail in his foot or ſome other miſchance. Then muſt he perforce buy, or hire another Horſe; and if he have not money enough to do ſo, then muſt he let her ride on his, and he trot by her ſide like a Lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key. By the way ſhe will ask for twenty things, for milk becauſe ſhe cannot away with their drink; for pears, plumbs, and cherries: When they come near a Town he muſt run before to chooſe out the beſt Inne: ever and anon as ſhe rides, ſhe will of purpoſe let fall her wand, her mask and gloves, or ſomething elſe, for him to take up, becauſe ſhe will not have him idle: When they are come home, ſhe will for a fortnight together, doe nothing elſe but gad up and down amongſt her Goſſips, to tell them how many gay and ſtrange things ſhe hath ſeen: all that hath paſſed by the way, in going and coming,
<pb facs="tcp:42603:23"/>but eſpecially of her good man, whom ſhe will be ſure to blame, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he did her no pleaſure in the world, and that ſhe poor ſoul, being ſick and weary, could not get him to help her, or to provide any thing for her that ſhe liked: And finally, that he hath had no more care of her, than if ſhe had been a meer ſtranger.</p>
               <p>But he (poor ſot) finding at his return all things out of order, is not a little troubled to ſet them in due frame again, and toyls ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly at his labour, that he may recover his charges which he hath been at in his journey. But ſhe, what for goſſiping, for pride, and idleneſſe, will not ſet her hand to any thing: And yet if ought go well: ſhe will ſay that it was through her heedfulnes and good huſwifery. If otherwiſe, then will ſhe ſcold &amp; lay the fault there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of on him, although it be her own doings. To be ſhort, having thus gotten a vein of gadding, ſhe will never leave it, and hereby the poor man will be utterly ſpoiled, for both his ſubſtance ſhall be waſted, his limbs through labour fill'd with aches, his feet with the gout, &amp; age comes on him before his time: yet as though this were not evil e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, ſhe will be continually brawling, ſcolding, &amp; complaining, how ſhe is broken through child-bearing. Thus is the filly man up to the ears in Lobs pound, being on each fide beſet with care and trouble which he takes for pleaſure, and therein languiſheth whiles he lives.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. The humour of a curſt Quean, married to a froward Husband.</head>
               <p>THe next humour that is incident to a woman, is when the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band having entred very young into Lobs pound, and there fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered himſelf by his too much folly, for a vain hope of tickliſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, which laſtet but for a year or two, hath matched himſelf with a very froward and perverſe woman (of which ſort there are too many) whoſe whole deſire is to be Miſtreſs, and to wear the breeches or at leaſt to bear as great a ſway as himſelf. But he being crafty, and withall crabbed, will in no wiſe ſuffer this uſurped ſoveraignty but with ſundry matters withſtands it. And there hath bin great ſtir and arguing about this matter between themſelves, and now and then ſome battles: but do ſhe what ſhe can, either with her tongue or hands, notwithſtanding their long controverſie, which hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps laſted at the leaſt theſe twenty years: he is ſtill victorious and holds his right: but you muſt think that his ſtriving for it all this
<pb facs="tcp:42603:24"/>while, hath been no ſmall trouble and vexation unto him, beſide all other aforeſaid euils. All which, or part thereof, he hath likewiſe endured. Well, to be ſhort, he hath perchance three or four children all married, and by reaſon of the great pains and travel that he hath taken in bringing them up, providing them portions, maintaining his wife, increaſing his ſtock, or at leaſt keeping it from being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed, and living with credit amongſt his neighbours: At laſt it may be he hath gotten the gout, or ſome other dangerous diſeaſe, and withall is grown old, and thereby feeble: ſo that being ſet, he can hardly riſe, through an ach that he hath got in his armes or legs: Then is their long war come to an end, and the caſe (as <hi>Ployden</hi> ſaith) clean altered: For his wife being younger than he, and as fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick as ever ſhe was, will now beſure to have her own will in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of his heart: Hereby the poor man which hath maintained the combate ſo long, is now utterly put down: his own children which before he kept in awe well enough, will now take heart to themſelves, and if he reprove them for their lewdneſſe and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſhe will maintain them againſt him to his teeeh, which muſt needs be a great grief unto him.</p>
               <p>But beſides all this, he is in doubt of his ſervants; for they like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe neglect their former duty and lean all together to their Miſtreſs: ſo that he poor man, which now by reaſon of his ſickneſſe, and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of body, hath more need of attendance than ever he had, ſhall have but very little or none at all: For though he be as wiſe and as carefull as ever he was, yet ſith he cannot beſtir himſelf to follow them as he was wont, they contemn and make no more reckoning of him, than if he were a meer fool.</p>
               <p>Then peradventure his eldeſt ſon, thinking that his father lives too long, will take upon him to guide the houſe, and diſpoſe all things at his pleaſure, as if his father were become an innocent, and could no longer look to things as he was wont: Iudge you whether the good man ſeeing himſelf thus abuſed by his wife, children and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, be grieved or not. If he purpoſe to make his Will, they will ſeek all means to keep him from doing it, becauſe they hear an ink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, that he will beſtow ſomewhat on the Pariſh, or will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath his wife ſo much as ſhe would have.</p>
               <p>To be ſhort, that they may make an end of him the ſooner, they will many times leave him in his Chamber half a day and more
<pb facs="tcp:42603:24"/>without meat, fire, or ought elſe, not one of them coming to ſee what he wants, or to do him any ſervice: his wife is weary of him by reaſon of his ſpitting, coughing, and groaning.</p>
               <p>All the love and kindneſſe which he had in former times ſhewed unto her, is quite forgotten; but this ſtrife for ſuperiority, and his crabbedneſſe towards her (when ſhe had juſtly moved him) this ſhe can ſtill as well remember, as when it was firſt done: Neither will ſhe ſpare to prate thereof to her neighbours: telling them that he hath been a bad man. and that ſhe hath led ſuch a life with him, that if ſhe had not been a woman of great patience, ſhe ſhould never have endured to keep houſe with ſo crabbed a churl.</p>
               <p>She will likewiſe boldly reproach, and twit him in the teeth with thoſe former matters, for it doth yet ſhrewdly ſtick in her ſtomach, that ſhe could not till now be Miſtreſs. But he that was wont to charm her tongue, and keep her under, who ſeeing him now in his diſtreſſe and weakneſſe, takes advantage, and continues his bad uſage: Seeing all his Children, which ſhould fear and reverence him, take part with their Mother, being taught and ſet on by her: ſeeing this (I ſay) and being no leſſe angry then grieved, he calls ſome of them in a rage, and when they are come before him, thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins he to his wife.</p>
               <p>Wife, you are ſhe, whom by the laws of God and man, I ſhould love and eſteem more than any thing elſe in the world and you on the other ſide ſhould bear the like affection to me: but whether you do ſo or not, I refer it to your own conſcience: I tell you I am not well pleaſed with your uſing me thus: I think you take me ſtill for the Maſter of the houſe as before you have done, but whether you think ſo or not, be ſure I will be Maſter while I live, yet you I thank you, do uſe me and account of me in very ſlight manner: I have alway loved you well, never ſuffered you to lack that which was meet: I have in like ſort loved, and alſo maintained your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and mine, according to my degree, add now both you and they do very unkindly requite me.</p>
               <p>Why (ſaith ſhe) What would you have us to do? We do the beſt we can, but you cannot tell your ſelf what you would have. The better we uſe you, and the more we tend you, the worſe you are, but you were never other, always brawling, and never quiet, nevee pleaſed full nor faſting: I think never woman was ſo long troubled with a croaked Peſtle as I have been.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:42603:25"/>
               <p> Ah Dame (ſaith he) leave theſe words I pray you: then turning him to his eldeſt ſon, he ſaid: Son, I have marvelled at your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour of late towards me, and tell you I am not well pleaſed therewith: You are my eldeſt, and ſhall be mine heir, if you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have your ſelf as a Child ought to do: But you begin already to take ſtate upon you, and to diſpoſe of my goods at your pleaſure: I would not wiſh you to be ſo forward, but rather while I live, to ſerve and obey me as it becomes you to do: I have been no bad fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unto you, I have nothing impaired or diminiſhed, but increaſt that which was left me by my Father, which if you do your duty to me (as I did mine to him) I will leave to you after my deceaſe as he left to me: but if you continue in your ſtubbornneſs and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, before God (I ſwear) I will not beſtow one penny or croſſe upon thee.</p>
               <p>Here his wife begins again to thwart him: Why, what would you have him do? it is impoſſible for any one to pleaſe you; he ſhall have enough to do that ſhall always tend you: I wis it is high time that you and I were both in Heaven, you know not your ſelf what you would have, I marvel what you ail. Well, well (ſaith he) I pray you be quiet, do not maintain him thus againſt me, but it is always your order.</p>
               <p>After this, the Mother and Son departing, conſult together, and conclude, that he is become a child again, and becauſe he hath threatned to diſinherit them, they reſolve that no man ſhall be ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to come and ſpeak with him: His ſon takes upon him more than before, being born out by his Mother; who together with him, makes every one believe that the poor man is become childiſh, and that he hath loſt both his ſence and memory.</p>
               <p>If any of his honeſt friends and former acquaintance, which were wont to reſort unto him, come now to ask for him, his Wife will thus anſwer them: Alas he is not to be ſpoken with, and when he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the cauſe thereof, doubting he is dangerouſly ſick: Ah good neighbour (ſaith ſhe) he is become an Innocent, even a Child again, ſo that I poor ſoul muſt guide all the houſe, and take the whole charge of all things upon me, having none to help me: but God be praiſed for all.</p>
               <p>In faith (ſaith the other) I am very ſorry to hear this, and do much marvel at it, for it is not long ſince I ſaw him, &amp; ſpoke with him, and
<pb facs="tcp:42603:25"/>then he was in as good memory, and ſpake with as good ſenſe &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as ever he did before. In truth (ſaith ſhe) he is now as I tell ye.</p>
               <p>Thus doth ſhe wrong and ſlander the poor man, which hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways lived in good credit, and kept his houſhold in very good order: but you may be well aſſured, that he ſeeing himſelf in his age thus deſpiſed and injured, and being not able to remedy himſelf, nor ſtir without help from the place where he is, thereby to acquaint his friends therewith, which might in his behalf redreſſe it, is not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle grieved, vexed, and tormented in his mind, with ſorrow and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: So that it is a great marvel he falls not into deſpair: For it is enough to make a Saint become impatient to be uſed thus by thoſe which ſhould obey ſerve and honour him. And in my opinion this is one of the greateſt corroſives that any man can feel: ſuch is the iſſue of this great haſte and extreme deſire to be in Lobs pound, where he muſt now remain perforce, till death do end (at once) both his life and languiſhing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. The humour of a Woman given to all kind of pleaſures.</head>
               <p>ANother humour incident to a woman by nature, is, when the husband (thinking that wedlock was of all eſtates the happieſt, and altogether repleniſhed with delight and pleaſure) becauſe he ſaw ſome of his friends, who for a while after they were married, were very cheerful &amp; jocund, never ceaſeth toyling and turmoyling himſelf till he hath gotten into Lobs pound, wherein he is preſently caught faſt like a bird in a net: for this compariſon, if we do examine the particulars thereof, doth very fitly reſemble his eſtate. The ſilly birds which flie from tree to tree and from field to field to ſeek meat, when they ſee a great deal of Corn ſpilt on the ground, think themſelves well apaid, and without any fear come hither to feed thereon, picking up the grains of corn, but alas they are deceived, for on a ſudden the net is drawn and they are all faſt tied by the legs, and thence carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a ſack or panier one upon another to the fowlers houſe, then cooped up in a cage. Oh how happy would they think themſelves, if they were again at their former liberty to fly whither they liſt, but they wiſh too late: yet were this all the evil that they ſhould indure, it were well, but (which is worſe) they ſhall ſoon after have their necks wrung off, &amp; their little bodies ſpitted to be made meat for men to eat.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:42603:26"/>
               <p> But they are therein far more ſimple than the Birds, for they being faſt in Lobs pound, and ſo beſotted with their own ſorrows, that they have no power to free themſelves: So likewiſe they have no will to do it. But to proceed; the wife not loving her husband, for ſome defect which is in him, that ſhe may have ſome colour for that ſhe doth, makes her mother and other friends which blame her for it, believe, that her husband is bewitcht; and by reaſon of ſome Sorcery, made for the moſt part impotent; hereupon ſhe complains of her ill fortune, reſembling it to thoſe, which having the Cup at their noſes cannot drink: mean while ſhe hath a ſweet heart in a corner, who is not bewitched, who uſeth her company ſo long, and with ſo little heed, that in the end her husband perceives it, and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into the vain of jealouſie, beats her well favouredly, and keeps a foul ſtir both with blows and words, ſo that ſhe not liking his u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, gives him the ſlip, but then is he clean out of patience, and ſo husbands in this taking are ſo mad, that they never lin ſeeking them, and would give half they are worth to find her again: who having thus plaid the pageant, and ſeeing her husbands humour, compacts with her mother, whoſe good will ſhe will be ſure to get by one means or other (whereas at the firſt ſhe will perhaps think hardly of her departure from her husband) ſhe doth I ſay, ſo handle the matter with her that ſhe will make the good man believe her daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hath been all this while at home with her, and that ſhe came to ſhun his bad uſage, who (had ſhe tarried with him till then) had been lamed for ever.</p>
               <p>Before God (quoth ſhe) I had rather you ſhould reſtore her again to me, than beat her thus without cauſe, for I know that you ſuſpect her wrongfully, and that ſhe hath never offended you: I wis I haue ſtraitly examined her about it, but if ſhe would have been naught, you did enough to provoke her: By Gods paſſion, I think few wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men could have born it. Well (it may be) that upon theſe or the like tearms he takes her again: it may be alſo that they are both deſirous to be divorced, each accuſing other, and ſeeking to winde themſelves again out of Lobs pound, but in vain. For either the cauſes that they alledge are not thought ſufficient by the Iudge, how hard ſoever they plead, but muſt of force continue ſtill together, are laughed to ſcorn of all that hear the cauſe: for if they be ſeparated, yet will not all this ſet them free, but rather plunge them in deeper
<pb facs="tcp:42603:26"/>than before, but neither of them can marry whiles the other lives, and their chaſtity ſo brittle (eſpecially hers) that hold it cannot, nor long endure.</p>
               <p>She who was wont to be ſo frolick, muſt needs continue ſo ſtill. Nay peradventure, being now without controlment, follows her evil and lewd life more freely than before: and whereas ſhe was but earſt a private Queene, ſhe is now common in the way of Good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, or elſe ſome luſty Gallant takes her into his houſe and ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters her by his noſe, which muſt needs be unto him an exceeding in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward grief, and an open diſgrace and ſhame in the eyes of the world; and which is worſe, he knows not how in the world to remedy it, but muſt perforce indure both, while this miſerable life doth laſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. The humour of a woman to get her Daughter a Husband, having made a little wanton eſcape.</head>
               <p>THe next humour that a woman is addicted unto, is, when a luſty young Gallant riding at pleaſure up and down the Countrey, but eſpecially to thoſe places of ſports and pleaſure where the fineſt Dames and dainty Girles meet, who can finely mince their Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, having their tongues trained up to all kind of amorous chat; in which delightfull exerciſes, this Youngſter both by reaſon of his youth, his looſe bringing up, and natural inclination, takes a great felicity in ſuch vain company: and ſo much the rather, becauſe he findes himſelf always welcomed, and kindly entertained to ſuch places, and the reaſon is the comelineſſe of his perſon, his ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able countenance, and queint behaviour: for whoſoever hath theſe good helps, ſhall want no favour at Womens hands. It may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that his parents are ſtill living: and he their onely joy, they having herhaps no Child but him, ſo that all their moſt delight is in maintaining him bravely. It may be alſo, that he is newly come to his Lands, and loves to ſee faſhions, though it coſt his purſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo largely. If any Gentlewoman offer any kindneſſe, he is ready to require it: and at length through long paſſing to many places, he lights on one that doth exceedingly pleaſe his eye, and inflame his heart: ſhe is perhaps Daughter to ſome Gentleman, ſome Citizen, or ſome worthy Farmer. Shee hath a clear com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion,
<pb facs="tcp:42603:27"/>a fine proportion, a wanton eye, a dainty tongue, and a ſharp wit; by reaſon of all which good gifts, ſhe is grown very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous. She hath been wooed, ſued, and courted by the braveſt Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants in the Countrey; of whom perhaps ſome one being more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and couragious than the reſt, hath offered her ſuch kindneſſe. as ſticks by the ribs a good while after, and would needs inforce this courteſie with ſuch importunity, that ſhe had not the power to reſiſt it: for a woman that hath her fine wits, if ſhe be withall of a cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſanguine complexion, cannot be ſo unkind, or ſo hard-hearted as to deny, or repulſe the petition of an amorous Friend, if he do any thing earneſtly proſecute the ſame. And (to be plain) be ſhe of what complexion ſoever, ſhe will be nothing ſlack to grant ſuch a ſuit.</p>
               <p>But to return to our purpoſe, by reaſon of her tender compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and kinde acceptance of his proffered ſervice, it ſo falls out ſhe hath plaid falſe, then is there no other ſhift but to keep it both ſecret and cloſe, and to take ſuch order as they beſt can, for ſmoothing up of the matter; he that hath done the deed, being a poor young man, though proper of body, and perhaps can dance very well, by which good quality he won her favour, and within a while after cropt the flower of her maidenhead: he (I ſay) after a week or two, and no further matter (leſt this privy, ſcape ſhould be openly known) is war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from coming any more to the houſe, or frequenting her company whatſoever.</p>
               <p>But now you muſt note, that ſhe being but a ſimple girle, between fourteen and fifteen years of age, nothing expert, but rather a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in ſuch matters, and having been but lately deceived, knows not her ſelf how it is with her: But her Mother which by long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience hath gotten great judgement, doth by her colour, her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of pain at her heart and ſtomach: with other like tokens, perceive it well enough, and having (as before I ſaid) caſhiered the Author of the action: then takes ſhe her daughter aſide, and ſchools her ſo that in the end ſhe confeſſeth that he hath been dallying with her, but ſhe knows not whether to any purpoſe or not. Yes (ſaith her Mother) it is to ſuch purpoſe, as by theſe ſignes I know very well, that you have thereby both ſhamed your ſelf, and all our friends, and ſpoiled your marriage quite and clean.</p>
               <p>To be ſhort, having ſomewhat chid her after the common order, for having no more reſpect nor care of her honeſty, (yet not chiding
<pb facs="tcp:42603:27"/>very extreamly, becauſe ſhe knows the frailty of youth by her own former experience) ſhe concludes thus comfortably: Sith it is done, and cannot be altogether remedied, ſhe will ſeek both to hide and ſalve the matter as well as ſhe can, charging her Daughter ta ſet a good countenance on it, leſt it ſhould bee ſuſpected, and to follow her counſell and commandement in all things: Whereupon the poor Wench willingly conſenteth, then the Mother proceeds thus:</p>
               <p>You know Maſter <hi>T. A.</hi> that cometh hither ſo often, he is you ſee a proper Gentleman, and a rich Heir, to morrow he hath appointed to be here again: Look that you give him good entertainment. and ſhew him good countenance. When you ſee me and the reſt of our Gueſts talking and diſcourſing together, ever and anon caſt your eyes on him, in the kindeſt and lovingeſt manner that you can. If he ſeem deſirous to ſpeak with you, be not coy, but hear him willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, anſwer him courteouſly. If he intreat love of you, tell him that you know not what it means, and that you have no deſire at all to know it; yet thank him for his good will; for that Woman is too un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courteous and uncivill, which will not vouchſafe the hearing or gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwering to thoſe that love her and wiſh her well.</p>
               <p>If he offer you money take none in any caſe; if a ring, or a girdle, or any ſuch thing, at the firſt refuſe it, yet kindly and with great thanks: but if he urge it on you twice or thrice, take it, telling him ſith that he will needs beſtow it on you you will wear it for his ſake. Laſtly, when he takes his leave, ask him when he will come again: Theſe inſtruments being thus given, and the plot laid for the fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of this kind fool into Lobs pound:</p>
               <p>The next day he cometh, and is on all hands more kindly wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and entertained: after dinner, having had great cheer, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther falls in talk with the other gueſts, and this frollick Novice gets him as neer to her Daughter as he can, and while the other are hard in chat he takes her by the hand, and thus begins to court her:</p>
               <p>Gentlewoman, I would to God you knew my thoughts. Your thoughts Sir (ſaith ſhe) how ſhould I know them, except you tell them me? It may be you think ſomething that you are loth to tell. Not ſo (ſaith he) yet I would you knew it without telling. But that (ſaith ſhe ſmiling) is impoſſible. Then (quoth he) if I might doe it without offence, I would adventure to tell you them. Sir (ſaith ſhe) you may freely ſpeak your pleaſure: for I do ſo much aſſure me of
<pb facs="tcp:42603:28"/>your honeſty, that I know you will ſpeak nothing that may procure offence.</p>
               <p>Then thus (ſaith he) I acknowledge without feigning, that I am far unworthy of ſo great a favour, as to be accepted for your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, friend, and lover, which are ſo fair, ſo gentle, and every way ſo gracious, that I may truly ſay, you are repleniſhed with all the good gifts that nature can plant in any mortal creature: But if you would vouchſafe me this undeſerved grace, my good will, diligence, and continual forwardneſſe to ſerve and pleaſe you ſhall never fail: but I would therein equal the moſt loyal lover that ever lived, I would eſteem you more than any thing elſe, and tender more your good name and credit than mine own.</p>
               <p>Good Sir (quoth ſhe) I heartily thank you for your kind offer, but I pray you ſpeak no more of ſuch matters, for I neither know what love is, nor yet care for knowing it: This is not the leſſon that my Mother teacheth me now adays. Why (ſaith he) if it pleaſe you, ſhe ſhall know nothing of it; yet the other day I heard her talk of preferring you in marriage to one Maſter <hi>G. R.</hi> How ſay you to that (quoth ſhe?) Marry thus (anſwers the Gentleman) if you would vouchſafe to entertain me for your Servant, I would never marry but onely rely upon your favour.</p>
               <p>But that (ſaid ſhe) ſhould be no profit to either of us both, &amp; beſide it would be to my reproach, which I had not thought you would ſeek. Nay (quoth he) I had rather dye then ſeek your diſcredit. Well Sir (ſaith ſhe) ſpeak no more hereof, for if my Mother ſhould perceive it, I were utterly undone. And it may be her Mother makes her a ſign to give over, fearing ſhe doth not play her part well.</p>
               <p>At the breaking up of their amorous Parley, he conveys into her hand a gold ring, or ſome ſuch toy, deſiring her to take it and keep it for his ſake: which at the firſt (according to her Mothers precepts) ſhe doth refuſe: but upon his more earneſt urging of it, ſhe is content to take it in the way of honeſty, and not on any promiſe or condition of any farther matter: when it was brought to this paſſe, the mother makes metion of a journey to be made the next morning, ſome ten or twelve miles off, to viſit, or feaſt with ſome friend, or to ſome Fair, or whatſoever other occaſion preſents it ſelf. To this moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they all agree, and afterwards ſit down to ſupper, where he is placed next the Daughter, who carries her ſelf ſo toward him with
<pb facs="tcp:42603:28"/>her piercing glances, that the young Heir is ſet on fire therewith: Well, morning comes: they mount on Horſeback, and by the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of them all: there is never a Horſe in the company that can carry double but his: So the gull is appointed to have the Maiden ride behinde him, wherefore he is not a little proud: and when he feels her hold faſt by the middle (which ſhe doth to ſtay her ſelf the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) he is even raviſhed with joy.</p>
               <p>After their returning home, which perhaps will be the ſame night the Mother taking the Daughter aſide, queſtions with her, touching all that had paſſed between the amorous Gallant, and her: which when her daughter had rehearſed, then proceeds the wily Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame thus: If he court thee any more (as I know he will) then make him anſwer that thou haſt heard thy father and me talk of marching thee with Maſter <hi>G. R.</hi> but that thou haſt no deſire as yet to be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried: if he then offers to make thee his Wife, and uſe any compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons of his worth and wealth as though he were every way as good as he, thank him for his good will and kindneſſe, and tell him that you will ſpeak with me about it, and that for thy own part thou couldſt find in thy heart to have him to thy Husband rather than any one elſe: upon this leſſon the daughter ſleeps, revolving it all night in her mind.</p>
               <p>The next morning ſhe walkes into the Garden and this luſty yonker follows; when having given her time of the day, he falls to his former ſuit. She wills him to give over ſuch talk, or ſhe will leave his company: Is this the love you bear me, (quoth ſhe) to ſeek my diſhoneſty? you know well enough that my Father and Mother are minded to beſtow me otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>Ah my ſweet Miſtreſs (ſaith he) I would they did ſo far favour me herein, as they do him: I dare boldly ſay and ſwear it, and without vain glory utter it, that I am every way his equall. Oh Sir, (anſwers ſhe) I would he were like you. Ah ſweet Miſtreſs (ſaith he) you dain to think better of me than I deſerve, but if you would further vouchſafe me that other favour, I ſhould eſteem my ſelf moſt happy. In troth Sir (ſaith ſhe) it is a thing that I may not do of my ſelf, without the counſel and conſent of my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, to whom I would gladly move it, if I thought they would not be offended: But it would be ſo much the better, if you brake the matter unto them; and be ſure, if they refer the matter to me,
<pb facs="tcp:42603:29"/>you ſhall ſpeed as ſoon as any. He being raviſhed with theſe words, and yielding her infinite thanks, trots preſently to the Mother, to get her good will.</p>
               <p>To be ſhort (with ſome little adoe) the matter is brought about, even in ſuch ſort as he would deſire: they are ſtraight way contracted, and immediately wedded, both becauſe that her friends fear that the leaſt delay will prevent all, and becauſe he is ſo hot on the ſpur, that he thinks every hour a year till it be done. Well, the wedding night comes, wherein ſhe behaves her ſelf ſo (by her Mothers counſell) that he dares ſwear on the Bible that he had her Maidenhead.</p>
               <p>Within a while after, it comes to his Friends ears, without whoſe knowledge he hath married himſelf, who are exceeding ſorry, knowing ſhe was no meet match for him, and it may be they have heard withall of his Wives humour: but now there is no remedy that knot is knit, and cannot be undone, they muſt therefore have patience perforce.</p>
               <p>Well he brings his fair Bride home to his own houſe, where (God wot) he hath but a ſmall time of pleaſure, for within three or four moneths after their marriage, ſhe is brought to bed: Iudge then in what taking the poor man is. If he put her away, his ſhame will be publick, ſhe grows common, and he not permitted to marry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain while he lives, and if he keep her ſtill, love her he cannot, ſuſpect her he will, and ſhe both hate him, &amp; perhaps ſeek his end: Finally, all the joys, pleaſures, and delights which before time they had, are all turned to brawls, banning, curſing and fighting, Thus is he hampered in Lobs pound, where he muſt of force remain, till death ends his lives miſeries.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. The humour of a woman being matched with an over kind Husband.</head>
               <p>THere is another humour incident to a Woman, which is when a Young man hath turmoyled and toſſed himſelf ſo long, that with much adoe, he hath gotten into Lobs pound, and hath perhaps met with a Wife according to his own deſire, and perchance ſuch a one, that it had been better for him to have
<pb facs="tcp:42603:29"/>lighted on another: Yet he likes her ſo well, that he would not have miſt her for any Gold, for in his opinion there is no Woman alive like unto her, he hath a great delight to hear her ſpeak, is proud of his match, and peradventure is withall of ſo ſheepiſh a Nature, that he hath purpoſed wholly to govern himſelf by her counſel and direction: So that if any one ſpeak to him about a Bargain, or whatſoever other buſineſſe, he tells them that he will have his Wives opinion in it, and if ſhe be contented, he will go thorow with it; if not, then will he give it over: Thus is he as tame and pliable as a Iack-an-Apes to his Reeper. If the Prince ſet forth an Army, and ſhe be unwilling that he ſhould go, who (you may think) will ask her leave, then muſt he ſtay at home, fight who will for the Countrey: But if ſhe be at any time deſirous to have his room (which many times ſhe likes better than his company) ſhe wants no Iourneys to imploy him in, and he is as ready as a Page to undertake them: If ſhe chide, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers not a word; generally, whatſoever ſhe doth, or howſoever, he thinks it well done.</p>
               <p>Iudge now what a caſe this ſilly Calf is in: Is not he (think you) finely dreſt, that is in ſuch ſubjection? The honeſteſt Woman, and moſt modeſt of that Sex, if ſhe wear the Bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, ſhe is ſo out of reaſon in taunting and controlling her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band: For this is their common fault, and be ſhe never ſo wiſe, yet becauſe a Woman, ſcarce able to govern her ſelf, much leſs her Husband, and all his affairs: For were it not ſo, doubtleſs God would have made her the head: which ſith it is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, what can be more prepoſterous, than that the Head ſhould be governed by the Foot? If then a wiſe and honeſt Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans ſuperiority be unſeemly, and breed great incoveniences, &amp;c. How is he dreſt (think you) if he light on a fond, wanton, and malicious Dame? Then (doubtleſſe) he is ſoundly ſped: ſhe will not ſtick to keep a ſweet-heart under his noſe; yet is he ſo blind, that he can perceive nothing, but for more ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſhe will many times ſend him packing beyond Sea about ſome odde errand, which ſhe will buzze in his eares, and hee will perform it at her pleaſure, albeit ſhe ſend him forth at midnight, in Rain, Hail, or Snow, for he muſt be a man fit for all weathers: Their children (if they have any) muſt needs be
<pb facs="tcp:42603:30"/>brought up, apparelled, fed, and taught, onely according to her plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: and one ſpecial point of their learning, is alwayes to make no account of their Father: If any of their children be daughters, ſhe will marry them according to her mind, to whom ſhe liſt, when ſhe liſt, and give with them what Dowry ſhe liſt, without acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him therewith, till ſhe have concluded the match, and then ſhe tells him not to have his conſent, but as a Maſter may tell his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, to give him direction how to behave himſelf to deal therein. Finally, ſhe orders all things as ſhe thinks beſt her ſelf, making no more account of him (eſpecially if he be in years) than men do of an old horſe which is paſt labour.</p>
               <p>Thus is he mewed up in Lobs pound, plunged in a ſea of cares and corroſives, yet he (kind fool) deems himſelf moſt happy in his unhappineſſe, where he muſt now perforce remain while his life doth laſt, and great pitty it were he ſhould want it, fith he likes it ſo well.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII. The humour of a Woman whoſe Husband is gone beyond the Sea, upon ſome buſineſs.</head>
               <p>ANother humour of a woman is, when the Husband hath been married ſome ſeven or eight years, more or leſſe, and as he thinks, he hath met with a good Wife as any man can have, with whom he hath continued all the aforeſaid time, with great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and pleaſures: But admit he be a Gentleman, and that he is deſirous to purchaſe honour by following Arms and in this humour he is reſolved to make a ſtep abroad, and not to tarry alwaies like a cowardly Drone by the ſmoak of his own Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: But when he is ready to depart, ſhe having her cheeks blubbered with tears, falls about his neck, culs, kiſſeth, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braceth him, then weeping ſighing, and ſobbing, ſhe thus begins to him:</p>
               <p>Ah ſweet Husband, will you now leave me? Will you thus depart from me, and from your loving Children, which know not when we ſhall ſee you again, or whether you ſhall ever come home
<pb facs="tcp:42603:30"/>again or no? Alas ſweet Husband go not: Tarry with us ſtill, if you leave us, we are utterly undone.</p>
               <p>Ah ſweet Wife (ſaith he) diſſwade me not from this enterpriſe, which concerns my Credit and Allegeance: for it is our Princes commandment, and I muſt obey: but be you well aſſured, I will not be long from you (if it pleaſe God.)</p>
               <p>Thus doth he comfort and quiet her in the beſt ſort that he can, and be ſhe never ſo importunate, be her teares never ſo many, her intreaty never ſo forcible, yet go he will, eſteeming his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown and Duty to his Prince and Countrey, more than Wife and Children, though next to it, he eſteem and love them chiefeſt of all other. And at his departure, he recommends them to the care and courteſie of his chiefeſt friends: Yet ſome there be whoſe tender hearts melt ſo eaſily with kind compaſſion that one of their wives tears, and the leaſt of their intreaties, will ty them ſo faſt by the leg at home, that they will not ſtir one foot frome her ſweet ſide, neither for Ring nor <hi>Keyſar,</hi> Wealth nor Honour. Theſe are Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and unworthy to be called Gentlemen.</p>
               <p>But to return to this valourous and brave minded Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, of whom we ſpake before; It may be, that either by the long continuance of the Wars, or by his miſ-fortunes, in being taken Priſoner, or ſome other lett, he comes not home in four or five years, and all that while there is no newes of him, you may be ſure that his Wife is a ſorrowful Woman, and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſurcharged with grief, being thus deprived of her loving Mate, and hearing nothing of his eſtate. But all things have an end, and ſhe ſeeing that in ſo long time, ſhe can hear no tidings of him, doth peremptorily conclude that he is dead. Then conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to live comefortleſſe in Widows eſtate, were an uncouth life, ſhe determines to marry her ſelf to ſome; one, ſo ſoon as conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently ſhe may: which will be ſoon enough; for a fair Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, if willing, can want no choice. Thus the former ſorrow is ſomewhat alaid, and within a while after, clean extinguiſht by the freſh delights, pleaſures, contents and ſolace, which this new choice doth yeeld. So that now her other Husband is wholly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, her Children which ſhe had by him little regarded and the Goods which belong to them, are ſpent on others, while the poor wretches want things needfull, but not blowes and hard uſage.
<pb facs="tcp:42603:31"/>To be ſhort, the tears which ſhe beſtowed upon her other Husband at his departure, are dried up, her imbraces vaniſhed. And whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhould ſee her with this ſecond Husband, and what kindneſſe ſhe ſhews him, would verily think that ſhe loves him far berter than ſhe did the firſt, who in the mean while is either taken Priſoner, or elſe fighting in extream hazard of his life.</p>
               <p>But in the end it chanceth ſo, that by paying his Ranſom (if he have been priſoner) home he comes, clean changed, through the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny troubles he hath had: and being come ſomewhat naer, fails not to enquire of his wife and children, for he is in great fear, that they are either dead, or in ſome great diſtreſſe. And doubtleſſe in the time of his Impriſonment, or other dangers, he hath oft thought, oft dreamed of them and oft ſorrowed for them, oft beſought God to preſerve and bleſs them. And that perhaps ſometimes, at the very inſtant when ſhe was in the others arms, toiyng and dallying, and in the midſt of her delights.</p>
               <p>Well, enquiring (as aforeſaid) he hears that ſhe is married again, then judge you with what grief he hears it. But his grief is boorleſſe, for now the matter is paſt remedy, if he have any care of his credit, any regard of his eſtimation he will never take her more though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the other, having his pleaſure of her, could be well contented either to reſtore her to him, or to leave her to any one elſe.</p>
               <p>She on the other ſide is utterly aſhamed, and her name ſtained with perpetual reproach: and neither he nor ſhe can marry whiles they live. Their poor children are likewiſe grieved and ſhamed at their Mothers infamy. Sometimes likewiſe it happens that for the wives cauſe the Husband being couragious quarrels, and perhaps combates with him, who being better than himſelf, doth either wound or kill him, and the occaſion hereof ſprung from their wives pride, becauſe (for ſooth) ſhe will take the wall of the other Wife or ſit above her: whom ſhe will in no wiſe ſuffer, nor looſe an inch of her eſtate, and hereupon the Husbands muſt go together by the ears.</p>
               <p>Thus the ſuppoſed bleſſedneſſe which he expected by plunging himſelf in Lobs pound, is turned into ſorrow, trouble, danger, and continuall diſcontent while life doth laſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:42603:31"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV. The humour of a Woman that hath been twice married</head>
               <p>THere is another humour belonging to a Woman, which is, when a Young man (having found the way into Lobs pound) meets with a Wife of like years, freſh, luſty, fair, kind, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious: with whom he hath lived two or three years in all delights, joys and pleaſures, that any married couple could have. Never did the one diſpleaſe the other; never foul word paſt betwixt them but they are almoſt ſtill colling and billing each other like a couple of Doves: And nature hath framed ſuch Sympathy berween them, that if the one be ill at eaſe or diſcontented, the other is ſo likewiſe. But in the middeſt of this their mutual love and ſolace, it chanceth that ſhe dyes, whereat he grieves ſo extreamly, that he is almoſt beſide himſelf with ſorrow: he mourns not onely in his Apparel, for an outward ſhew, but unfeignedly in his very heart, and that ſo much, that he ſhuns all places of pleaſure and all company, liues ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily, and ſpends the time in daily complaints and moans, and bitterly bewailing the loſſe of ſo good a Wife, wherein no man can juſtly blame him, for it is a loſs worthy to be lamented, and a Iewel, which whoſoever hath, is happy (but this happineſs is very rare.)</p>
               <p>To be ſhort, his thoughts are all on her, and ſhe is ſo firmly printed in his mind, that whether he ſleep or wake, ſhe ſeems alwayes to be in his ſight: but as all things have an end, ſo here had ſorrow. After a while, ſome of his friends having ſpied out a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond match, which as they think is very fit for him, do prevail ſo much with him, through their perſwaſions, that he accepts it, and marries himſelf again, but not as before, with a Young Maid, but with a luſty Widdow, of a middle age, and much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, who by the trial which ſhe had of the firſt Husband, knows how to handle the ſecond: But that ſhe may do it the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſhe doth not preſently diſcover her humour, till ſhe have tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly markt how he is inclined, what his conditions are, and
<pb facs="tcp:42603:32"/>what his nature is: which finding it mild, and kind, and very flexible (the fitteſt mould to caſt a Fool in) having now the full length of his foot, the ſhewes ſhe her ſelf what ſhe is, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>masking her diſſembling malice; her firſt attempt is to uſurp Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioriry and to become his Head, and this ſhe obtains without great difficulty, for there is nothing ſo laviſh as a ſimple and well natured young man, being in ſubjection, that is married to a Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, eſpecially if ſhe be (as the moſt of them are) of a perverſe and crabbed nature. I may very well compare him to an unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Wretch, whoſe ill fortune is to be caſt into ſome ſtrong Priſon, under the keeping of a moſt cruel and pittileſſe Iaylor, that is not moved to compaſſion, but rather to great rigour, in beholding the miſeries of this poore Wretch, whoſe only refuge in this diſtreſſe, is to pray unto God, to give him patience to endure this croſs, for if he complain of his hard uſage, it will afterwards prove worſe.</p>
               <p>But to proceed. This jolly Widdow will within a while grow jealous, fear and ſuſpect that ſome other Dame hath part of that which ſhe ſo earneſtly deſired, and wherewith ſhe could never be ſatiſfied, ſo that if he glut not her inſatiate humour, ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſhe conceiveth this opinion; If he do but onely talk, nay, (which is worſe) look on any other Woman, For the by her good will would be alwayes in his arms, or at the leaſt in his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: For as the Fiſh which having been in water, that through the heat of the ſummer is half dried up, begins to ſtick full of mud, ſeeks for freſh water, and having found it, doth willingly remain therein, and will in no wiſe returne to his former place: Then ſo an old Woman, having gotten a young Man, will cling to him like Ioy to an Elme.</p>
               <p>But on the other ſide, a young man cannot love an old Woman, howſoever he doth diſſemble, neither is there any that more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangers his death: for it is with him, as with one that drinketh mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty wine, who if he be thirſty, feels nothing while he is drinking, but at the end of his draught, he feels ſuch a diſpleaſing taſt, that it doth almoſt turn his ſtomach.</p>
               <p>But if young men in no wife can fancy old Women, what love thinke you young Women can bear to old Men, when beſides the ſundry imperfections of their Age, which are ſo loathſome, that it
<pb facs="tcp:42603:32"/>is impoſſible for a freſh, young, tender Damſell, (be ſhe never ſo vertuous) to endure their company, much leſſe the kiſſes and imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the perſon which hath them: All the luſty Gallants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts will not fail to uſe whatſoever devices and means poſſible for the horning of the old Dotard: hoping that ſhe will be eaſily won to wantoneſſe: And ſurely they ground this hope on great liklihood; for ſith it is no difficult exploit to graft the like kindneſs on a young mans forehead, who is able in far better meaſure to feed his Wives appetite, and the hath therefore more cauſe to be true to him, it may ſurely ſeem no great matter to perform the like piece of ſervice with this other unfortunate Dame.</p>
               <p>But now to return to our young man, yok'd (as before I ſaid) to this old Widdow, I thus conclude, that his eſtate is moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: For beſides the danger of his health, and beſides the ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, nay rather ſervitude which he lives in, this third evil, (I mean his Wives jealouſie) is alone an untolerable torment unto him: So that be he never ſo quiet, never ſo deſirous to content her, never ſo fearfull to diſpleaſe her, yet cannot he avoid her brawls, objections, and falſe accuſations of Lewdneſſe and Diſloyalty: For an Old Woman infected with Iealouſie, is like a Helliſh Fury.</p>
               <p>If you go to any of her Friends about buſineſſe, yea, to the Church to ſerve God, yet will ſhe alwayes think the worſt, and aſſure her ſelf, that he playes falſe, though indaed he be never ſo continent: Who whatſoever he pleadeth in his own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, yea, though hee prove himſelf blameleſſe, by ſuch rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as ſhe can by no reaſon confute, yet will not all this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie her: Such is the perverſeneſſe of her ſtubborn, crabbed, and malicious nature, made worſe by Dotage and Raging Iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie: For being privie to her owne defects, and knowing that he by reaſon of his youth and hanſomeneſſe may perchance fall in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with a young Dame, thinking withall that a young man, when he may have ſuch a match, will be loth to leave it for a worſe or preferre ſowr verjuice before ſweet wine, ſhe concludes perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily in thoſe ſuggeſtions as before. Loe here the iſſues of this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes turning into Lobs pound, and intangling of himſelf again, when he had once gotten out to his former liberty, which if he once more looked for, he is mad; for he muſt now perforce conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue
<pb facs="tcp:42603:33"/>there while life doth laſt, which by this means, will be far ſhorter, and he look far older, having been but two yeares marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with this old crib, than if he had lived ten years with a young wife.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. The humour of a young Woman given over to all kind of wantonneſs.</head>
               <p>THere is yet another humour that a Woman is ſubject to, which is, when an unfortunate young Man having long la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to get into Lobs pound, and having in the end obtained his deſires, doth match himſelf with a luſty wanton Young Wench, which without fear of him, or care of her own credit, takes her pleaſure freely, and withall ſo over boldly, and unadviſedly, that within a while her Husband perceives it, who thereupon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not a little inraged, doth in the heat of his impatience, after much brawling on both ſides, roughly and deſperately threaten her, thinking thereby to terrifie her, and make her honeſt by compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: But that makes her worſe, for where as before ſhe did it for wantonneſs, now will ſhe do it for deſpite: and what with the one and the other, be ſo inflamed, that were ſhe ſure to be killed for it, yet would ſhe not leave it: Which he perceiving watching her doings ſo narrowly, that in the end he ſees her ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heart come cloſely to his houſe, then being on fire with fury, runs haſtily to ſurprize him, and enters his Wives Chamber, with full purpoſe to kill him, though he had ten thouſand lives: But judge you what a taking the poor young man is in, ſeeing himſelf thus ſurprized, and looking for nothing elſe but preſent death, becauſe he hath nothing to defend himſelf. But ſhe, for whoſe ſake he hath incurred this danger, doth kindly free him by this ſtratagem: for as her Husband is ready to ſtrike or ſtab him, ſhe catcheth him haſtily about the middle, crying out, Alas man what do you mean? While ſhe thus ſtayes her Husband, the yonker betakes him to his heels, running down the ſtairs amain, and out of the doors, as if the Devil were at his tail, and after him the good man, as faſt as he can drive. But when he ſees that he cannot overtake him, he turns back in a like rage,
<pb facs="tcp:42603:33"/>to wreak his anger on his Wife. But ſhe dreading as much gets her haſtily (before his return) to her Mother, to whom ſhe complains of his cauſſeſs ſuſpition, and Devilliſh fury, juſtifying her ſelf, as if ſhe were not the Woman that would commit ſo lewd a part: But her Mother ſifting the matter narrowly, her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confeſſeth her fault, but to make it ſeem the leſs, ſhe tells her a large tale of the Young Mans importunity, who for ſo long time together, did continually trouble her, and whither ſo ever ſhe went he would be ſure to follow her, begging pitifully her love, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, that ſhe had often ſharply anſwered him, and flatly deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Suit, yet could ſhe not for all that be rid of him: ſo that in the end ſhe was inforced for her own quietneſſe to grant his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt: She repeats withall, how kindly and intirely he loves her, how much he hath beſtowed on her, how many foul journeys he hath had for her ſake, in Rain and Snow, as well by Night as Day, in danger of Thieves, in peril of his Life, and how nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly he eſcaped her Husband the laſt time, ſo that for very pitty and compaſſion, ſhe was moved to favour him: And no Woman could be ſo hard hearted, as to ſuffer ſo true and kind a Young Man to languiſh for her love, and dye unregarded: for on my life Mother (ſaith ſhe) if I had not yielded, he would have died for thought.</p>
               <p>The Mother hearing her Daughter to ſay thus, accepts her an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for current, and thinks that ſhe hath ſufficiently juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſelf; but to prevent further ſcandall, and to appeaſe her angry ſon in law, and reconciled her Daughter unto him by caſting a miſt before his eyes, ſhe takes this courſe, ſhe ſends for her ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Goſſips and Companions. whoſe counſels in like caſes ſhe doth uſe: They comming at the firſt call, and being all aſſembled, either before a good fire (if it be Winter) or in a green Arbour (if it be Summer) one of them noting her daughters heavy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, demands the cauſe thereof: Marry (ſaith ſhe) ſhe hath had a miſchance, about which I have made bold to trouble you, and crave your advice: With that ſhe recounts all the whole matter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, but ſhewing the true cauſe of her Husbands anger: To bee ſhort, ſhe hath ready two or three pottles of Wine, and a few junkets, which they preſently fall aboard on, that they may the ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter give their ſeveral verdicts afterwards; mean while they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb facs="tcp:42603:34"/>the Young Woman, bidding her aſſure her ſelf, that her Husband is more perplexed than ſhe, and that I know by mine own experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, for my Husband and I were once at variance, but he could never be quiet till we were made friends. In good faith Goſſip (ſaith another) and ſo ſerved I mine. Another <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> makes a motion to ſend for the Young Gallant that is ſo true a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to her Goſſips Daughter, that his preſence may cheer her; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> away her Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy.</p>
               <p>This Motion doth her Mother faintly contradict, but in the end moſt voyces prevail, he is ſent for and comes with a trice, then there is much good that, many a rerpoach and kind ſcoff given the poor Husband: And to mend the matter, comes in the Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid, who was privy to all the former cloſe packing between her Miſtreſs and her Sweet heart, and for her ſilence and imployment, in furthering both their contents, ſhe hath gotten a good new gown and ſomewhat elſe.</p>
               <p>It may be her Maſter hath ſent her abroad about ſome buſineſs, or perhaps ſhe coyns an excuſe of her ſelf, thereby onely to make a ſtep abroad to ſee her Miſtreſs, and to bring her ſome newes how all things go at home: She hath no ſooner ſet her foot within the room where they are, then one of them ask how her Maſter doth? My Maſter (ſaith ſhe) I never ſaw a man in that taking: I dare ſay, that ſince yeſterday morning when this miſ-fortune happened, he hath not eaten one crumme, drunk one drop, or ſlept one wink all yeſternight. To day he ſat down to dinner, and put one bit in his mouth, but could not ſwallow it, for he ſpit it out preſently, &amp; ſate a good while after in a dump: In the end ſtriking his knife on the table, he roſe haſtily, and went into the Garden, and immediately came in again: To be ſhare, be is alltogether out of temper, and can reſt no where: He doth nothing but ſigh and ſob, and he looks like a dead man: hereat they laugh apace, and to be ſhort, they determine that two of the chief of them, ſhall go and ſpeak with him the next morning, and that when they are in the middeſt of their talk, the reſt ſhall come in afterward. The Mother with her two Goſſips, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this plot, do proceed in the matter. And next morning finding him in his dumps, one of them gently asks him what he ailes: hereto he anſwers onely with a ſigh: whereupon ſhe takes occaſion thus to ſpeak: In good faith Goſſip, I muſt chide you,
<pb facs="tcp:42603:34"/>my Goſſip your wives mother told me I know not what of a diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement between your wife and you, and a certain fond humour that you are fallen into: I wis I am ſory to hear it: And before God you are not ſo wiſe as I had thought you had been, to wrong your wife thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhout a cauſe, for I durſt lay my life there is no ſuch matter. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this good day (ſaith another) I have known her ever ſince ſhe was a little one, both Maid and Wife, and I never ſaw but well by the woman: And in good ſooth it grieves me to the very heart, that her name ſhould now come in queſtion without cauſe: Before God, you have done the poor woman that diſgrace, and ſo ſtained her good name, that you will never be able to make her amends. Then ſteps in the Chamber-maid with her five eggs In good faith (ſaith ſhe) I know not what my Maſter hath ſeen, or whereon he doth ground his ſuſpition, but I take God to my wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that I neuer ſaw any ſuch matter by my Miſtreſs and yet I am ſure that if there were any ſuch thing, I ſhould ſee it as ſoon as another. Gods body, Drab (ſaith he, all inraged) wilt thou face me down of that which my ſelf ſaw? Oh Goſſip, (quoth the one of the Dames) God forbid that every man and woman which are alone together, ſhould do evil. I deny not (ſaith the Chambermaid) that the villanous knave hath long ſued unto my Miſtreſs for ſuch a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but by my honeſty Maſter, I know that there is never a man alive, whom ſhe hates more: And rather than ſhe would commit any ſuch folly with him, ſhe would ſee him hang'd and be burned her ſelf: I marvel how the Devil he got into the houſe.</p>
               <p>Here the other Goſſips come in, one after another, and each gives her verdict: In good faith Goſſip (ſaith one) I think that next your wife, there is never a woman in the world, that loves you better than I do: and if I knew or thought any ſuch matter, I would not lett to tell you of it. Surely (ſaith another) this is but the Devils work to ſet them at variance, for he cannot abide that husband and wife ſhould live well together. In good faith ſaith the third, the poor woman doth nothing but weep, By Chriſt (quoth the fourth) I fear it will coſt her her life, ſhe grieves and takes on in ſuch ſort. Then comes the Mother weeping and crying out making as though the would ſcratch out his eyes with her nails; exclaiming in this ſort.</p>
               <p>Ah curſed Caitiff, woe worth the time that ever my Daughter
<pb facs="tcp:42603:35"/>matcht with thee, to be thus ſhamed and ſlandered, and have her name ſpotted without cauſe. But ſhe is well enough ſerved, that would take ſuch a baſe churl, when ſhe might have had ſundry good Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen. Ah good Goſſip (ſaith another) be not out of patience.</p>
               <p>Ah Goſſip (ſaith ſhe) if my Daughter were in fault, by our good Lord, I would kill her my ſelf. But think ye I have no cauſe to be moved, when I ſee my child, being guiltleſſe, thus uſed? With that ſhe flings out of doors in a rage, and all the Goſſips come upon him thick and threefold, who is ſo full of ſundry thoughts, and ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and troubled, that he knows not whereon to reſolve, nor what to ſay.</p>
               <p>In the end they growing ſome what calmer, promiſe if he will, to undertake the reconciling of him and his wife, which he moſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſireth them to do.</p>
               <p>They accordingly perform it, ſo that all controverſies are ended, all ſtrife ceaſed, the matter huſhed up, and his wife taken home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; who taking greater courage by the ſucceſs hereof, and being now clean paſt ſhame. will grow far bolder in her villany, than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And he door Meacock, on the other ſide, having his courage thus quailed, will never afterwards fall at odds with her, for fear of the like ſtorm, but will ſuffer her to have her own will in all things, and be in a manner ſubject to her, ſpending the remnant of his life in care, fear, diſcontent and grief, his goods waſting he knows not how, and himſelf become alaughing ſtock to all that know him.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>☞ An Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>Thoſe moſt <hi>Famous Pills</hi> ſo <hi>eminently</hi> Known in moſt Parts of <hi>Europe</hi> to be the only <hi>True, Safe,</hi> and <hi>Effectuall Medicine</hi> againſt the DROPSY and SCURVY, with all other <hi>Sharp, Salt,</hi> and <hi>Watry Humours;</hi> and Helps many other deſperate <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> Cleanſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Womb</hi> of all <hi>Superfluous Humidity,</hi> that often is the Cauſe of <hi>Non Conception,</hi> are ſtill faithfully Prepared by <hi>W. Sermon</hi> Doctor of Phyſick and Phyſitian in Ordinary to <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> and Sold by the Said Doctor and Mr <hi>Edward Thomas</hi> Bookſeller at the <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in <hi>Little Brittaine &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42603:35"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42603:36"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42603:36"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
